<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A looking glasse for maried folkes Wherein they may plainly see their deformities; and also how to behaue themselues one to another, and both of them towards God. Set forth dialogue-wise for the more tastable and plainnesse sake. By R. S.</title>
            <author>Snawsel, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12570</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22886</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106906</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842614</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842614</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7282</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12570)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7282)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 728:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A looking glasse for maried folkes Wherein they may plainly see their deformities; and also how to behaue themselues one to another, and both of them towards God. Set forth dialogue-wise for the more tastable and plainnesse sake. By R. S.</title>
                  <author>Snawsel, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[116] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by N. O[kes] for Henry Bell and are to be sold at his shop on Holburne Hill neere the crosse Keyes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>R.S. = Robert Snawsel.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A(-A1) B-G H⁴(-H4).</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through, and some pages stained; some leaves tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriage --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7282:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7282:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LOOKING GLASSE FOR Maried Folkes. Wherein they may plainly ſee their deformities; and alſo how to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue themſelues one to another, <hi>and both of them towards God.</hi> Set forth Dialogue-wiſe for the more taſtable and plainneſſe ſake, By <hi>R. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROVERBS. 11.29.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He that troubleth his owne houſe, ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite the winde, and the foole ſhall be ſeruant to him that lendeth.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROVERBS. 12.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>A vertuous woman is the crowne of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band: but ſhe that maketh him aſhamed, is as corruption to his bones.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>N. O.</hi> for <hi>Henry Bell,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop on Holburne Hill neere the croſſe Keyes. 1610.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7282:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7282:2"/>
            <head>THE AVTHOR TO the gentle Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, the ſpeciall cauſe indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing me to take in hand this worke, and to bring my can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle lighted into the glorious Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of this age, and to publiſh the ſame to the view of this famous common-wealth, was, that I haue ſeene &amp; heard, with griefe of heart, in many places whither I haue come, wicked and vnquiet liuing betweene man &amp; wife: the which cauſed me many a time to conſult with my ſelfe, how I might be a meanes to reforme the ſame. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered and thought with my ſelfe, that many wanted meanes to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled
<pb facs="tcp:7282:3"/> one to another, and that there was no booke extant of this ſubiect in Engliſh; and that for want of meanes many haue liued igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly, and ſo of neceſſity wickedly and diſcontentedly together, to the diſhonor of God, the offence and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill example of others, the loſſe of their credits, the waſting of their goods, the corrupting of their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and ſeruants; and finally to the conſuming of their owne bodies; yea many to the deſtroying of their ſoules for euermore. The conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of theſe things moued me not to delay, but ſpeedily to ſeeke out a remedy for them. And I pray God grant, that euery one that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the aforeſaid diſeaſe, when as this booke ſhall come to their hands, may apply it effectually vnto themſelues, that ſo they may expell the poiſoned malice of their cankered hearts. And all theſe pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents I would haue to marke, that the
<pb facs="tcp:7282:3"/> more they giue way vnto their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or rather vnnaturall affections, the more they ſhall be tainted with the horrible vices whereto they are addicted. And againe, the more they are infected with them, the more ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous poyſon their children ſhall draw from them, not onely whiles they are in their mothers wombe, but alſo much more afterwards by their euill examples. And howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it is little regarded that children can be infected with the parents diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition while they are in the wombe: yet dayly experience doth ſhew, that as they are formed and proportioned in body much like vnto their parents, ſo likewiſe in their nature and affections. Now therefore though thou haſt ſmall regard of thy ſelfe, yet for thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens ſake, which are the fruit of thy body, take heed, obſerue and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe good counſell herein contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; which if thou doeſt, I make no
<pb facs="tcp:7282:4"/> doubt but thou ſhalt be a meanes to ſaue both thy ſelfe &amp; many others: And moreouer, pondering theſe things deeply with my ſelfe, as I ſaid, I called vnto remembrance a Dialogue betweene two women to this effect, written in Latine by the reuerend learned man <hi>Eraſmus;</hi> and thinking it was not in Engliſh, I thought to publiſh the ſame in our mother tongue for the benefite of my countrymem: but after conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering further, that that onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned women, yea and that they might attaine to all that which hee counſelleth there, and yet be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; I haue added thereunto the ſubſtance of faith and repentance, with diuers other particular poynts and examples, though briefly; which being practiſed, are ſufficient to life eternall. And moreouer, leſt men by reading the former part of this booke, which teacheth the duty of wiues, ſhould domineere too much
<pb facs="tcp:7282:4"/> ouer them, I haue ſhewed them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the later part thereof, the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which they owe to their wiues, drawne from plaine proofes, reaſons and arguments of holy Scripture; ſo that they may both learne how to behaue themſelues each to other, and both of them to God, as they ought. And now if thou ſhalt reape profite from thence, as I hope thou ſhalt, except the fault be in thy ſelfe, giue glory to God, &amp; counſel to thy neighbours, as time and oportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is offered: and in ſo doing, I doubt not but God will giue a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vnto thee &amp; thy directions; and by this meanes thou ſhalt be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of a publicke and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all good, not onely in making good parents, but they by thy meanes alſo ſhall make good children, and good ſeruants: and this by Gods bleſſing ſhal ſucceſſiuely go on from age to age, euen to the end of the world: and ſo by this meanes good
<pb facs="tcp:7282:5"/> parents which are ſcarce, ſhall bee multipled to the increaſe of Gods Church, and the flouriſhing eſtate of the common-wealth. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther know this, that good parents are ſpeciall inſtruments to make godly children, and good ſeruants; and godly children and good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants will make religious men and women; and religious men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth make a flouriſhing church, and famous common-weale, ſet forth Gods glory, and eſtabliſh the Princes kingdome. Therefore I pray thee conſider, and lay it vnto heart, what a common and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all good this peace-making is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene married couples. Therefore by this premiſed, euery one may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily ſee how neceſſary, comfortable, and commodious this little booke may bee through Gods bleſſing, to all ſorts of men (high and low, rich and poore, religious and prophane) that ſome may teach, and ſome may
<pb facs="tcp:7282:5"/> learne, and all reape profite one by another. And now gentle reader, if thou finde any ſlips herein, as haply thou maiſt, I pray thee couer them with thy courteſie. Accept of my good wil, &amp; receiue that with thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to God which may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to thy ſelfe; and if I ſhal heare that it ſhal be courteouſly receiued, and carefully practiſed, it ſhall bee a meanes through Gods fauour, to ſtirre me vp to attempt a greater worke, that ſhall be more profitable both for the Church of Chriſt, and my deare country, for the wealth of both which I onely deſire to liue, and to haue maintenance to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt my loue and duty which I owe vnto them.</p>
            <p>But becauſe I will not bee tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the preface, I will conclude, leſt I weary thee before thou come to the Conference. Onely this I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of thee, that thou wilt not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begin to reade the booke, but
<pb facs="tcp:7282:6"/> reade it to the end. And howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſome things may ſeeme vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorie vnto thee at the firſt: yet I feare not but in fine thou ſhalt finde it profitable and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable. And thus I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thee and all thy good exerciſes to the bleſſing of the Almighty.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Studious of thine as of mine owne quiet and profite,</hi> Robert Snawſel.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:7282:6"/>
            <head>A LOOKING GLASSE FOR MAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIED FOLKES: <hi>OR</hi> A profitable Conference, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene foure women and one man, touching their behauiours toward God and their husbands, and what they ought <hi>to bee; and alſo the dutie of husbands, toward their wiues.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="dramatis_personae">
               <p>The foure womens names are,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Abigail,</hi> the fathers ioy.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Eulalie,</hi> wel-ſpoken.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Xantip,</hi> a ſcold.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Margerie,</hi> a proud malapert.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ben-ezer,</hi> an helper.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eulaly.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OOD Morrow (neighbor <hi>Xantip</hi>) how do you to day? did you ſee my goſſip <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xantip.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>No, I ſaw her not to day: but mee thinks you are fairer
<pb facs="tcp:7282:7"/> then ordinary.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eulal.</speaker>
                  <p>What, do you begin to frump me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>No truly you ſeeme to mée to bée very ſmug.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eulal.</speaker>
                  <p>Peraduenture my new gowne ſets a gloſſe on my face.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I promiſe you you ſay true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, I haue not ſeene a goodlier a great while: I take it to bee made of Engliſh wooll.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>The wooll indeed is from En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, but it was died in Venice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Truely it is a moſt gallant gowne, the ſoftneſſe of it paſſeth ſilke: and what a fine purple colour is it of?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>It is true, I like it well indeed: but looke, who comes yonder?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is</hi> Margerie, <hi>whom you aſked for. Oh huge, how braue is ſhée? you haue onely a new gowne, but ſhee is new from toppe to toe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abigail.</speaker>
                  <p>And yet, I feare me, her ſoule is as old as <hi>Adam;</hi> and as filthy as the Serpent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Where were you that we ſaw you not before now?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>Little had you thought that I
<pb facs="tcp:7282:7"/> had bene ſo neare you, till you ſaw me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>No, for if I had, I would not haue ſworne ſo, as I did.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas I heard thee with griefe, and thought to haue told thee of it at time conuenient: but were you not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid leſt God ſhould ſee you, and heare you ſweare ſo horribly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I know well, that God ſeeth all things, but he is mercifull.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>And as he is mercifull, ſo alſo is he iuſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Welcome</hi> (Margerie) <hi>welcome.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>God a mercie good <hi>Xantip;</hi> how doſt thou?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Better to ſee you ſo freſh and well liking; mee thinks you are too too braue, your gown is moſt ſtately made, your neckerchiefe is of the fineſt cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricke, your ſtomacher is moſt gallant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wrought, and euery thing about you is ſo in print, that it doth mee good to looke vpon you.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>Woman, I may ſpeake it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs here, I will haue it ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the more is my griefe, that I cannot haue it ſo too.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you neighbours talke no
<pb facs="tcp:7282:8"/> more of thoſe things; why ſhould wee buſie our minds ſo much about this out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward apparell, which onely ſets out the body, and many times makes vs forget both God and our ſelues? Therefore I pray you (good neighbours) let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard this outward decking leſſe, &amp; the inward adorning of our ſelues more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What ſhall wée haue of you? a Puritane?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you <hi>Margerie,</hi> vſe no more ſuch ſcoffing ſpeeches.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And I pray you</hi> Abigail <hi>tel mee, doe you not thinke better of your ſelfe, then of any of vs?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>If you aske me to be bettered by my ſpeech, I will tell you what I thinke of my ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Truly I do,</hi> Abigail.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>I think in my conſcience, that I am a poore, ſinfull, and miſerable wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, in my ſelfe not worthy to liue vpon the earth; onely in and by Chriſt Ieſus, I hope to bee made eternally happy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eulal.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What, are you poore and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable? haue you not riches &amp; the world at will? and haue you not a louing hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,
<pb facs="tcp:7282:8"/> which makes much of you?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>Alacke <hi>Eulaly,</hi> thou art an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ciuill woman, I muſt needs ſay, but yet thou ſpeakeſt very carnally. What is all my riches, if I had 10000 times more then I haue, if that I bee not rich in Chriſt Ieſus? and what though I could rule the whole world, which way I would, if I haue not peace of conſcience? and what if I haue a louing husband, if I haue not a good husband?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Are you not rich in Chriſt? haue you not peace of conſcience? and haue you not alſo a louing and good husband?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe you proteſted, that you asked me to be bettered by me, I will make my caſe knowne vnto you in your eare. It is many times thus with me; when I thinke vpon my riches, and the aboundance of wealth, which God hath beſtowed vpon my husband and me; then ſathan ſuggeſteth euill moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in my heart, and my corrupt affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons break forth in my life, ſo that often I thinke better of my ſelfe then I ought; and that I may neglect to worke with my hands, and that I may haue this and
<pb facs="tcp:7282:9"/> that faſhion of apparell, becauſe other of my calling haue the ſame: and that I may eate this dainty thing or that; and that I may either ſit vp idly in the night, or lye longer then ordinary in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. And on the other ſide, while I thus pride my ſelfe in my apparell, and walke idly out of my calling, and pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per this ſinfull carcaſe with delicious fare, I haue not reſpect vnto ſome of my poore members, nay vnto Chriſts members, as I ought. I ſpeake this to my ſhame, that ſelfe loue is ſo much in me, which quenches the ſpirit of God, and depriues me many times of his fauour, and the excellent graces of his ſpirit, &amp; then my conſcience is troubled and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted; and then it is ſuch a griefe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me that I haue not a good husband, howſoeuer I confeſſe indeed I haue a louing husband.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What meane you by a good husband?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>By a good husband I meane a religious husband, which ſhould be my partener, and helper, not onely in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily and worldly things, but eſpecially in ſpiritual and heauenly, that we might
<pb facs="tcp:7282:9"/> draw Chriſts yoke equally together: that ſo in and through Chriſt wee might bee glorified together. I tel you neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, you will hardly beleeue, what a comfor it would bee vnto mee, if hee would tender my ſoule as he doth my body, nay if he would tender his owne ſoule. Indeed he will not be againſt any good thing I doe, I thanke God for it; but here is my griefe, that he will not bee partener of the good with mee, which is the cauſe, when I am ſicke or afflicted in conſcience, (as many times I am humbled for my ſins, I bleſſe God for it) then, I ſay, he cannot miniſter ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall comfort to me. Onely this he wil ſay, how doſt thou wife? or God helpe thee: which I take kindly: but alas it is farre from that, which the Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts men vnto; namely, that they ſhould dwell with their wiues, as men of knowledge; that is, if the woman be ignorant as the moſt are, he ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct and informe her in the waies of the Lord; if ſhe heare any thing preached, or at publicke diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whereof ſhee ſtands in doubt, ſhee ſhould aske her husbande iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:7282:10"/> at home, and he ſhould be able to reſolue her; he ſhould be able through God to comfort her in affliction, and to reioyce with her in proſperity: I do not meane any outward or fleſhly ioy, ſo much as that, which is ſpirituall and heauenly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What is that, which you two are whiſpering together of ſo long? I doe not think but it was about ſome religious matters, for</hi> Abigail <hi>loues to talke of nothing elſe; &amp; mee thought I heard now and then a ſound of ſome holy words. My husband is much like vnto her, they would haue bene very well matched together.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>Me thinkes young women ſhould not flout at any, much leſſe at their husbands or elders.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I pray you goſſip tell vs, what is the practiſe of your husband, I haue heard great commendations of him.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>I warrant you hee will not miſſe a Sermon, yea many times he will haue mee with him againſt my will, when I had rather bee walking abroad in the fields, or elſe ſit and talke with ſome of my neighbours: but ſomtimes
<pb facs="tcp:7282:10"/> I meete with him; for I am ſo long time a dreſſing of me, that he is glad to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, or elſe he ſhould loſe the beſt part of the Sermon. And when hee comes home, he wil pray, and make ſuch a long repetition of that which was preached, &amp; then ſuch a ſeueral examination of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one concerning the points deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that my heart grudges many times againſt him; and if it were not more for ſhame of the world, then for feare of him, I would tell him on both ſides, that he troubles both himſelfe and vs more then he needs. But ſometimes I get me out, as ſoone as euer we come in, and other ſometimes I lay the fault vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my memory, when he doth aske me, when I could, if I would, tell him; and then afterwardes hee goes to praier a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and euerie morning he will be ſure to haue vs together at prayer; ſo after ſupper there muſt a chapter bee read at the leaſt; and euery one muſt tell ſome thing, either what the meaning of ſuch a verſe is, or at leaſt repeate ſome verſe ouer that was read: and then he goes to prayer againe, and is ſo long commonly, that he make me
<pb facs="tcp:7282:11"/> ſo weary with kneeling, that ſometimes I am forced to ſit, and ſometimes to leane and kneele againe, and ſometimes I am almoſt a ſleepe; ſo that he makes me wiſh many wiſhes, that I will not vtter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You haue vttered too much of your own euil diſpoſition; truly I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell that you &amp; ſuch as you are doe not feare leſt the ground ſhould open her mouth and ſwallow you vp, or the houſe fall vpon your heades, or the Diuell to fetch you quicke to hell, for this intollerable profaneneſſe, contempt, and abhominable wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; that it will not onely ſuffice you to abuſe your Chriſtian husband, but God alſo and his worſhip, in ſuch a hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible maner. I dare aſſure thée, it doth grieue me at the heart; and if it were not that I receiued ſome ſtrength and and comfort by the holy practiſe of your husband, I thinke I ſhould haue fallen into a ſwound. Oh how doth it gréeue mée that ſuch a good man is troubled with ſuch a bad wife! But ſeeing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing comes to paſſe without Gods, prouidence, I hope it is onely to exerciſe his patience, and that hee beeing croſt
<pb facs="tcp:7282:11"/> héere with thee for a time, might liue without thee in glory for euer.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, but mee thinkes you are very earneſt, and no leſſe preciſe. It would be irkſome to any I thinke, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to haue any pleaſure, but to be euer exerciſed, as ſhee ſaid her husband was.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aibg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I tell thee my deare</hi> Eulaly, <hi>that it is the pleaſanteſt &amp; heauenlieſt life in the world, the which doth ſolace the ſoule, &amp; reioyce the heart of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian vnſpeakeably; and there is no life of God in them, which leade not this life.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, but do you thinke none ſhall bee ſaued but thoſe that doe ſuch things?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verily I thinke, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it is, that is ignorant of God &amp; his wil, and without faith, cannot be ſaued. And againe, whoſoeuer it is, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowes the will of God, and will obſtinatly ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contemn y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> practiſe of it in others, or neglect it in them ſelues, is in the ſtate of damnation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>Shee is euer of the minde of Maiſter <hi>H.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I know, that it is not only our
<pb facs="tcp:7282:12"/> mind, but the mind of the holy Ghoſt, and of all Chriſtians, that are called to the knowledge of Gods grace; and I wiſh in heart, that it were your mind, and if it pleaſed God, the minde of the whole world. For if they did know certainely, that all thoſe that are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of God, or contemptuouſly will ſcoffe at the practiſe of holy duties in others, or neglect it in themſelues, are in the ſtate of damnation, they would ſoone change their minds, and ſay, We fooles haue bene deceiued; and ſo no doubt, many of neglecters will become practitioners, and in ſteed of contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Gods people, and their practiſe, would become frequenters and louers of their heauenly ſociety.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>I promiſe you, you ſay very well, I thinke there bee but few women can ſay ſo much.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nay will you beleeue me, I thinke in my conſcience, there are not many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in our towne can ſay ſo much. I wonder how you haue thus growne in knowledge within theſe few yeares.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>I promiſe you, the more that I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider of her words, the more I maruel.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7282:12"/>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I will lay my life, that our</hi> ſir Iohn, <hi>nor</hi> ſir William <hi>of</hi> B. <hi>cannot ſay ſo much without booke; it is pitty y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you were not coupled to a preacher.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>The greater is their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and the more ſhall bee my pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, if my practiſe be not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my knowledge; &amp; therefore my heartes deſire and prayer to God is, that as hee doth increaſe in me knowledg, ſo hee would giue me humility, and power to obey, that which I know.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Indéed you ſay true. For I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith, that he which knowes his maiſters wil, and doth it not, ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>O neighbour <hi>Eulalie,</hi> if you would but practiſe that which you know, I ſhould loue you better then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I did: for then I hope you would be a Chriſtian indeed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why, what will you make of me? haue you known me thus long, and yet do you think y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am not a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>It is not ſuch an eaſie matter to be a Chriſtian. But be not offended with me, I will tell you what I thinke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7282:13"/>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What thinke you, I pray you tell me?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>I thinke you be an honeſt ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill woman, and a Chriſtian in name, but not in nature and in deed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why, I was baptized, and go to Church, and I doe not mocke at the Preachers and profeſſors, as ſome do; I am neither whore nor thiefe; I pay e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one their owne; I cannot abide to ſweare, &amp;c. I hope you cannot accuſe me of deceiuing any, nor of lying: what manner of people will you make Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas <hi>Eulalie,</hi> alas, I perceiue you would be counted a Chriſtian, and that hitherto you haue thought your ſelfe to be one. I muſt needs tell you truly, that you haue ſcarce ſet one foote in Chriſtianity: for all which you haue ſaid, you may do, and yet bee damned.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Here is a ſharpe ſentence.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you tell me the right way, that ſo I may walke in the direct path which leadeth vnto Chriſt; that ſo I might become one with him, and an heire of his kingdome.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>With all my heart. The firſt
<pb facs="tcp:7282:13"/> ſtep is repentance, and faith in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>What is repentance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Diuines doe define it in two words, mortification and viuifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that is, a dying to ſin, and liuing to righteouſneſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>And by what meanes muſt this be wrought in vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By the powerfull preaching of the word of God, which breaketh and ſofteneth the hard &amp; ſtony heart, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth the ſoule, and woundeth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience for ſinne which it hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt the God of heauen, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it vnfeignedly to deſire peace and reconciliation with him in his Sonne Chriſt; with a deteſtation of all the ſins which he hath committed, and a reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to leade the reſt of his life holy and vnblameably, as in the ſight of God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>What is Faith?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is the worke of the Spirit of God in vs, which doth aſſure vs of the free pardon of our ſins, and of the loue and fauour of God in Chriſt Ieſus, with all the benefites that come with him; as it
<pb facs="tcp:7282:14"/> is written: It is the Spirit of God that beareth witneſſe vnto our ſpirits, that we are the ſonnes of God: and ſo it is that ſpirit which cauſeth vs to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend and apply the mercies of God in Chriſt, and our ſelues, to the obedience of his word.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray God that we may ſo do.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If you haue an vnfeigned de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire (as you ſeemed to me to haue) God hath promiſed to giue you power, if you will giue your endeuour therewithall: and ſo I commit you to his grace.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea but Goſſip, I pray you tell me, who gaue you this new gowne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Your minde is more ſet vpon my gowne, then vpon thoſe heauenly matters which</hi> Abigail <hi>ſpoke of.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>I will lay twenty ſhillings, that <hi>Abigail</hi> hath almoſt made her a Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritane.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You thinke you may now talke your pleaſure; when ſhée was here, you had not a word: ſhe tooke you downe I trow.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope if you haue a new gowne, we may without offence ſpeake of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Shal I tel you how it is with me?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7282:14"/>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Truly</hi> Abigails <hi>words were ſo gracious, that I could willingly haue heard her, though ſhe ſhould haue ſate with vs all this day; her words are ſo ſauoury to my ſoule, that me thinkes we ſhould not put them out of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance with theſe outward things.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>Well <hi>Margery,</hi> if ſhe will not tel me who gaue her her new gown, do you tel me what coſt your neckerchiefe a yard.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I thinke your minde runs thus vpon theſe outward things, when you are at praier and at Sermons.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>It is good to ſpeake the truth; it doth ſo indeed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That ought not to be by no meanes: for thereby you much diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor God, and hinder your ſelfe, that the word cannot profite you.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea but will you tell me, who gaue you your gowne?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why, who, I pray you, ſhould giue honeſt wiues any ſuch things but their huſbands?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>And I pray you <hi>Margery,</hi> who gaue you yours?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7282:15"/>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My huſband alſo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>O happy women that happen on ſuch husbands! For my part, I would I had bene married to a toad-ſtoole, when I maried with my <hi>Ben-ezer.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O fie woman, what a wiſh is that? if</hi> Abigail <hi>had bene here, you would haue vext her to the heart; and I tell you truly, that you grieue me not a little. For I remember well, what ſhe ſaid, and I hope ſhall do, whiles I liue; namely, that we which profeſſe our ſelues to be Chriſtians, ſhould adorne the Goſpell of Chriſt by our holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation. And againe, ſhe ſaid, that the Apoſtle exhorts that our words ſhould be gracious and poudred, that they might miniſter grace to the hearers.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea you are happy, you haue no cauſe to ſpeake or complaine, that haue all things you ſtand in need of.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I thanke God we two do agrée, and I am ſorry that you two cannot, but that euery foote you are falling out.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>I thinke I ſhall neuer fall in with ſuch a fellow: you ſee how ragged<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he lets me go: I would I were dead, if I be not aſhamed many times to go out
<pb facs="tcp:7282:15"/> a doore, when I ſee how finely other women are dreſſed, that are married to farre poorer husbands then mine is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Well</hi> Xantip, <hi>well, I pray thée be contented; and if thou loueſt me, nay if thou loueſt God or thy ſelfe, marke well what our good neighbour</hi> Abigail <hi>hath ſaid out of the Apoſtle</hi> Paul, <hi>that the woman ought to be in ſubiection to her huſband. And againe, the orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of a woman lies not in gay apparell, or in any ſetting out of herſelfe to ſight, as S.</hi> Peter <hi>teacheth: for I remember that I heard awhile ago at a Sermon, that the ornament of a woman conſiſted in chaſte and honeſt conditions; and that the ornament of the minds or ſoules of godly women, was loue, méekneſſe, faith, and patience, &amp;c. And further, that it is the guiſe of drabs &amp; harlots to prancke and pricke vp themſelues to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueigle mens affections. Now then as for vs, that would be counted honeſt &amp; religious matrons, we are neat inough, if we be cleanly, and can pleaſe our huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, but this good man of mine is ſuch a niggard, that he will not allow
<pb facs="tcp:7282:16"/> me wherwithall I may go handſome, but prodigally he ſpends my portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which, though I ſay it, was no little one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If I were as thou art, I would haue better things, or elſe the houſe ſhould be too hot for him. My huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band would not willingly let me haue ſuch and ſuch a thing, but I trow hee ſhall neuer goe to praier quietly, nor haue a cheerefull looke till I haue it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, but my husband doth not only keepe me without ſuch trim attire as you haue, but he will not let me haue that which is neceſſary, but ſpend that we haue in tipling and ſwilling, at dice, and cards, and amongſt whores and harlots.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Good words, good words: I think you ſurmiſe, and ſay more then is true.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>It is too true which I ſay; and moreouer when hee comes home well whitled in drinke at mid-night, after he hath bene a long while waited for, hee ſnorts like a ſwine when he is laied: and ſir reuerence caſts vp his drunken gorge in the bed, to ſay no more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O</hi> Xantip, <hi>you make my heart ake to heare you. Therefore marke this,
<pb facs="tcp:7282:16"/> that when you doe thus diſgrace your huſband, you ſhame you ſelfe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>I would I were dead, if I had not rather ſleepe with a ſow, then lye by his ſide.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg,</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But do you rattle him vp at his comming home?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, I handle him as hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues, I make him know that I haue a tongue in my head.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And what ſaith he againe?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>At the firſt he is as loud as I, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to beare mee downe with great words.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But do you neuer fall from ſcolding to ſcuffling?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>Once wee were fallen out ſo farre, that a little more would haue made vs fight out-right. Hee got vp a great cudgell, and ſhaked it at me, threatning me with thundering ſpeeches.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O lamentable liuing betweene man and wife!</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Waſt thou not afraid then</hi> Xantip?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>Afraid? no: on the other ſide, I tooke vp the treuit; and if he had but touched me with a finger, he ſhould wel
<pb facs="tcp:7282:17"/> haue ſeene and felt, that I would haue laid about me luſtily with both my hands.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I promiſe you, I commend you for your manly courage; you had got a new kinde of target, when you had the treuit, you did but lacke your di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaffe in ſtéed of a iauelin.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>I would haue made him haue knowne, that hee had met, and medled with his match.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O neighbour, this ſhould not be ſo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>What tell you me of it? if hee will not vſe me as his wife, I will not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate him as my husband.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But</hi> Paul, <hi>as I ſaid before, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, that wiues ſhould be in ſubiection to their huſbands with all reuerence, and not to be check-mates with them: and</hi> Peter <hi>ſets downe</hi> Sarah <hi>for an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to women, who called her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>We haue heard of theſe things before as well as you: but the ſame <hi>Paul</hi> I trow, teacheth, that husbands ſhould loue their wiues, as Chriſt did his Church.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7282:17"/>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Well, let him firſt do his duty, and then I will do mine.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>But yet when the caſe ſtands thus, I thinke it is the wiues part to yeeld firſt to her husband.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Huſband, quoth ſhe, marrie in good time; if he be a huſband that makes no more account of me, then of his kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin girle.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>But in kindneſſe Xantip tell me: did he, when you ſtood ſo ſtoutly to him, leaue off to threaten you blowes?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Did he? yes, and it was beſt for him too, I trow, or elſe as I am an honeſt woman, I ſweare to you, I would haue be laboured my fellow well and ſoundly.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>O terrible manniſh woman! I did not thinke that thou hadſt bene of ſuch a peremptory ſpirit. Thou doeſt not remember that he hath power ouer thee, and that thou ſhouldeſt let thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire be ſubiect to thy husbands.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It was well done</hi> Xantip; <hi>hold him out ſtill at ſtaues end, yéeld him not an inch, leſt he take an ell: let him not crow ouer thée.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>You need not giue her ſuch wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb facs="tcp:7282:18"/> counſell; what, will you haue all the world to exclaime on our ſexe, and cry out vpon women kind?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why, none but men will ſpeake againſt vs; and if they do, we can giue them two words for one in the hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt manner.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Me thought you ſaid your huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band left his threatning: me thinks then <hi>Xantip,</hi> in all equity and conſcience, you ſhould ceaſſe your ſcolding.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I mind not to leaue it yet.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>What does hee, I pray thee, whileſt thou art ſcolding?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What? ſometimes he ſléepes, flugge as hee is; ſometimes hee fals a laughing; ſometimes he takes his fid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, which hath ſcarce three ſtrings, and thereon he ſtrikes with his fidling ſtick as loud as he can, that hee may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with drowne the noiſe of me.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>I am ſure, this behauiour of his angers thee to the heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It grieues me indéed to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry guts, and I ſo chafe ſometimes that I can hardly hold my hands.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you good neighbour hold your tongue, and giue me leaue to
<pb facs="tcp:7282:18"/> ſpeake my mind a little to you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Say on hardly, and ſpeake your pleaſure.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſhall be as bold with me when you pleaſe: me thinkes we two for old acquaintance ſake ſhould be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bold &amp; familiar one with another.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You ſay true. For truly we haue bene play-fellowes from our cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles; and of all that euer I had, there was none that euer I loued better then you.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                  <p>Well then, this I ſay in loue that I haue towards you ſtill, and my requeſt is euen as you loue me, to hearken vnto me. You are maried now vnto your huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, what manner of man ſoeuer hee be, you haue no liberty to change him for another, or caſt him off. In old time indeed, when couples could not agree, diuorcement was permitted &amp; appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as an extreme remedie, but now that is quite aboliſhed. <hi>Ben-ezer</hi> muſt bee your husband, and you <hi>Xantip</hi> his wife, till one of you dye.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A vengeance on them, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they be, that haue taken away that law and liberty from vs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7282:19"/>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Take heed what you ſpeake, you wot not what you ſay, nor whom you curſe. It is Chriſts pleaſure I tell you, &amp; no other mans, that it ſhould be thus hence-forth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I can hardly beléeue it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly <hi>Xantip</hi> it is as I ſay, and therefore cry Chriſt mercy for thy curſed blaſphemy, and ſtudy to agree with thy husband henceforward, by applying thy ſelfe vnto his quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Is it in my hands to make my huſband a new man?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>I can tell you <hi>Xantip,</hi> wee wiues may do much either in making or mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our husbands.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xan.</speaker>
                  <p>Do you and your husband agree ſo well together?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, now, God be thanked, wee liue in peace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By your owne ſaying it ſeemes, that you could not well agrée hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>I muſt needes confeſſe to thee, though I take ſhame to my ſelfe, the fault moſt commonly was mine. For I was, as many other yong women are,
<pb facs="tcp:7282:19"/> proud &amp; diſdainfull, ſcorning that my husband ſhould reproue mee; idle and careleſſe, ſeldome, or neuer, ſeeking to pleaſe him; but rather thought that hee ſhould ſtoope and ſeeke to me; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times I would be lumpiſh and low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; and if at any time he ſpake vnto me any thing which pleaſed me not wel, I would ſnap him vp ſhrewdly, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere him croſſely; with ſhame I may ſpeake it, God forgiue me: yet after, as I grew in yeares, I grew in experience, and comming acquainted with mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and modeſt matrons, they gaue mee graue and ſage counſell, which I obeied, and was much bettered by it: ſo that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, there was neuer any tempeſt, I thank God. But yet as it fals out commonly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt married folks, ſome little clouds aroſe which might haue made a ſtorme, except I had obſerued and practiſed the wiſe &amp; Chriſtian counſel of my louing religious neighbour <hi>Abigail,</hi> which made the cloudes to vaniſh, and my huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band as meeke as a lambe. For I conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that euery man hath his qualities, &amp; euery woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her infirmitie. I thought with my ſelfe how I might behaue my
<pb facs="tcp:7282:20"/> ſelfe beſt towards my husband for both our goods: and whiles I was weighing ſeriouſly theſe things, and reuoluing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in my minde, theſe ſentences of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture came to my remembrance. A ſoft anſwere ſtaieth wrath. And againe, A word ſpoken in due place, is like apples of gold with pictures of ſiluer. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: In many words there cannot want iniquity, but he that refraineth his lips, is wiſe. And againe, A wiſe man waits his opportunity, but a foole ſpeaketh what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer commeth to his mind. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, that which our Sauiour ſaith, that we ſhall giue account of euery idle word at the day of iudgement. And againe: That by our words we ſhall be iuſtified, and alſo condemned. And moreouer, the wiſe and gracious words of <hi>Abigail</hi> to king <hi>Dauid,</hi> came to my mind, whoſe words were ſo perſwaſiue and pithy, that they ſtaied his furie, what time hee was reſolute, and at the point to commit a great and horrible ſlaughter. And on the other ſide, I conſidered that we wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are apt to ſpeake, and how the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Iames</hi> willeth vs to bee ſwift to heare, and ſlow to ſpeake. Hereupon I
<pb facs="tcp:7282:20"/> gathered what a grace and goodly or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament it is for a woman to ſpeake wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſeldome, in modeſtie, and vnder correction: and therefore I reſolued to pray continually, that God would ſet a watch before my lips, leſt I ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend in my tongue: which though it be but a little member, yet, as the Apoſtle ſaith, if it be once kindled, is ſet on fire of hell.</p>
                  <p>Theſe, &amp; ſuch like ſayings of the holy Ghoſt ſwaied with me, and droue me to this conſideration, that though my tongue be one of the leaſt members of my body, yet if it were not rightly vſed. I might offend the moſt by it; I might much diſpleaſe my husband, and hurt my neighbours, &amp; deſtroy my own bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy &amp; ſoule for euer (all which ought to be more deare vnto me then all the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and pleaſures in the world.) And on the other ſide, if my tongue were rightly ordered, I might much glorifie God, beautifie his Goſpell, and adorne my Chriſtian profeſſion; ſpeake in the behalfe, and for the credit of my huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; and for the good of my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours: and therefore I praied vnto God,
<pb facs="tcp:7282:21"/> that hee would open the doore of my mouth, and giue me vtterance &amp; wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that when I ſpeake, my words might be directed by his Spirit, to put life and power into them, and ſeaſon them with wiſedome, and to make them forceable, gracious, and ſauoury in the eares of the hearers. So that to conclude, alwaies after I would be carefull what, and when to ſpeake, the manner how, and to whom, yeelding that reuerence to my husband, that is due to him. And I tell thee <hi>Xantip,</hi> theſe things wrought ſo with him by the bleſſing of God, that ſince I doe not remember that euer we haue had a croſſe word.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I promiſe you, I like your ſpéech paſſing well. Well, now I wiſh in my heart, that I, and all other women in the world, were of your minde: we may ſee what it is to kéepe company with thoſe that are wiſe and godly. I thinke our neighbour</hi> Abigail <hi>did you more good then euer any woman did; and I thank God, you haue done me more good then euer any woman hitherto hath done.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>I reioice greatly that God hath
<pb facs="tcp:7282:21"/> made me an inſtrument to doe you any good, or any other. And this I pray you neighbour, if there bee any good done vnto you by me through Gods mercy, ſhew the fruits thereof in a holy life. For I may tell you, be it ſpoken now to the glory of God, there were few that euer thought you would haue bene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, you were ſo lauiſh of your tongue, and ſo fierce, that you would haue ſcared one with your words.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We may ſee the power of the Almighty, who can make of the lyon a lambe, and that a little child ſhould play vpon the hole of the aſpe: and therefore I pray you, pray vnto God for me; yea and that alſo, when you are met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with</hi> Abigail, <hi>and the reſt of your Chriſtian friends, that God would go on with his good worke which hée hath begun in me.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>That is my duty. And to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get you in my praier, were to forget my ſelfe vnto God. I pray you alſo, take all the means that may helpe you forward, &amp; renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce whatſoeuer may hinder you. You heard what holy and heauenly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes <hi>Margeries</hi> good husband vſed;
<pb facs="tcp:7282:22"/> vſe you the ſame, though ſhee neglected and loathed them. In any caſe caſhiere her company, and the fellowſhip of ſuch, til you be ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, or ſhe better: for now ſhe is a perillous woman, her euill words and rotten ſpeeches will corrupt good manners, and quench your good motions: her religious husband is much vexed with her, euen as iuſt <hi>Lot</hi> was with the vncleane Sodomites. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, I am to aduiſe you, not to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maied for thoſe that will mocke you for your profeſſion, and becauſe they ſee you begin to make conſcience of your carriage, who vſe to ſay, that we are a holy ſiſter-hood, and preciſe fooliſh women; which prattle and chat wee know not what. Beare them with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and bee ſlow, yet ſure, when you ſpeake, eſpecially in the cauſe of Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bleſſed bee God for this your loue and good counſell: I hope I ſhall make vſe of it, as God ſhall enable me. I pray you now ſhew me ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular directions how I and my huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band may beſt liue together in mutuall loue.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Firſt of all I ſay to you, that many
<pb facs="tcp:7282:22"/> times loue is cleane loſt betweene cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, before they well know one the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the maine reaſon of it is, becauſe they obſerue not one anothers qualities, and apply themſelues accordingly: and another, becauſe they continue in ſtrife when they are fallen out, and do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times make vp the breach. And the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why they are backeward to make peace one with an other, ariſeth from the ſtoutneſſe of their hearts, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proud and ſtiffe, will not ſtoope one to another; which breedeth heart-bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings betwixt them, and inward grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging &amp; murmuring one at another: and therefore theſe curſed ſeeds of diſſentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and diſcord, being caſt once into the heart by the Diuell, will ſpring vp not only to roots, but trees, &amp; wil hardly or neuer be holpen, if at the firſt they bee not ſpeedily pluckt vp by the roots.</p>
                  <p>Now then marke the vſe of this: you are yet but a young woman, and haue bene maried but a while, and I ſee with griefe, that there haue bene bitter iars betwixt you; and now you for your part, are deſirous to haue peace, and liue in amity with him, that ſo you
<pb facs="tcp:7282:23"/> might paſſe your liues with mutual ioy. What therefore is paſt let it bee forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; and not onely forget, but forgiue all vnkindneſſe. And if at any time your husband beginne, either vpon ſome cauſe or no occaſion to contend, anſwere him mildly, and with all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty and meekeneſſe: take heed that you put no fuel to the fire of his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, for if you doe, it is a thouſand to one but the flame will burne you both. The tender twig is ſoone broken, but if it grow vnto a tree, it cannot be ſtird without an axe: which muſt cut it down. So likewiſe the nature of man is ſoone pacified with a ſoft and gentle anſwere; but if it be aſperate with bitter ſpeeches, nothing will aſſwage it, till it haue had his courſe, which is ſometimes vnto the deſtruction both of man and wife; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the mighty axe of Gods word come in the mouth of his Miniſter, and cut it downe. Therefore it behooues vs in the beginning to labour, what wee can, to agree one with another, and to ſtrengthen our affections againſt euill diſpoſitions, and to holy actions. Now the only way to compaſſe peace, is, that
<pb facs="tcp:7282:23"/> wiues be buxom and obedient to their husbands, and to vſe them kindly with gentle behauiour. Now whereas ſome women ſtand vpon their pantofles, that is, either vpon their gliſtering beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, their proper perſonage, great porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and rich parentage; alas it is nothing to leſſen their loyalty and ſubmiſſion to their husbands. And that man that ſets his loue vpon his wife, for theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things eſpecially, ſhall know, that as beauty paſſeth, his loue will paſſe with it; and as riches waſt, his loue will languiſh: and as her parents die ſo, his loue will bee buried in obliuion with them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xantip.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Good goſſip, tell mee, what way went you to worke to win your husband?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eulal.</speaker>
                  <p>I told you a little before: but to the end, that you may the better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it, and follow me, I wil tell you againe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xantip.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If I can, I will doe my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to the vttermoſt, through the helpe of God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>I make no doubt but that God wil ſtrengthen then you to any good worke,
<pb facs="tcp:7282:24"/> if you call vpon him for his aide, and take thoſe meanes which hee hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the accompliſhing of the ſame.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Well, I will.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Firſt then this was my care; when hee was pleaſed, how I might keepe in with him: and when hee was angrie, how I might appeaſe him. And this was one maine thing that I would continually aime at, to behaue my ſelfe humbly and meekly towards him, both in word and deed; alſo I would carry my ſelfe cheerfully toward him, and I would looke vp and downe, that there ſhould bee nothing that might offend him. I alſo obſerued his diſpoſition and inclination. Moreouer I had reſpect vnto times and ſeaſons, that his diet ſhould bee prouided in due time; and that he ſhould haue ſuch delicates, as were moſt comfortable for his heart, and pleaſant to his mouth; and ſo by this meanes I won both him and his loue vnto me; whereas before me thought he was as cruell as a Lyon, and terrible as a Dragon. Therefore I conſidered what thoſe do that take in hand to tame
<pb facs="tcp:7282:24"/> Lyons, and Elephants, &amp;c. which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be maſtered with ſtrong hand; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they that goe to the Elephant haue a ſpeciall care that they bee not clad in white; and they that goe to Buls, that they be not araied in redde; becauſe it hath bene found by experience, that thoſe creatures by theſe colours, are made wilder and fiercer; and alſo Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gres by the ſound of Timbrels, by report are ſo enraged, that they rend themſelues in peeces; So they that breake horſes haue their tearmes, their ſmackings, whiſtlings, and clappings, whereby they make their ſtout nature tame. Why then <hi>Xantip</hi> conſider I pray you, how much more ſeemely and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary it it, that we women ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint our ſelues with ſuch courſes, whereby we may win our husbands to goodneſſe; by whom we ſhould haue the greateſt comfort and defence next vnder God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is true: ſay on, I pray you, ſay on.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eulal.</speaker>
                  <p>Hauing obſerued theſe things, I applied me to his nature, and I had great care that nothing ſhould be done
<pb facs="tcp:7282:25"/> that might diſpleaſe him; nor nothing left vndone, that might offend him. Not onely of my ſelfe had I this care, but of all that was in in the houſe; and that not onely in great matters, but alſo in the leaſt</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xantip.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But how would you apply your ſelfe to him that would neuer tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry within doores, or come euery while drunken home?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Stay a while, I will ſpeake of that by and by. Firſt I will ſhew you forth my behauiour towards my hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, becauſe you deſired to know it. When he lookt at any time very ſad, &amp; there were no fit time to ſpeak to him, I would not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laugh &amp; dally with him, and play the tom-boy, as many women are wont to doe in ſuch a caſe, but I put vpon me a ſad countenance alſo, and lookt heauily; for euen as a looking glaſſe if it be a good one, doth ſhew the countenance of him that glaſſes himſelfe in it: So it beſeemes an honeſt wife to frame her ſelfe to her husbands affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and not to be merry, when he is melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, nor iocund, when he is ſad, much leſſe flire when hee is angry. And if at
<pb facs="tcp:7282:25"/> any time he were ſtird, I would either pacifie him with gentle ſpeech, or giue way to his wrath, till it were ſomewhat alayed; or elſe I would keepe ſilence, til there were fit time for clearing my ſelfe, or aduiſing him with reuerence and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion. This courſe alſo I tooke; if at any time he came drunken home, I would not then for any thing haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him a foule word, but I would cauſe his bed to be made very ſoft and eaſie, that he might ſleepe the better, and by faire ſpeeches get him to it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Héere are fetters for the legs, and yoakes for the neckes of women: muſt they crouch on this manner to their curriſh and ſwiniſh husbands? If I had ſuch an one, as he behaued him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe like a ſwine, ſo I would vſe him like a beaſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eulal.</speaker>
                  <p>I had thought we had bene ridde of your company.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I ſtood behind, and heard you ſo long, that I could no longer hold my peace. Are you a woman, and make them ſuch diſhclouts and ſlaues to their husbands? Came you of a woman, that you ſhould giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no prerogatiue, but
<pb facs="tcp:7282:26"/> make them altogether vnderlings?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you be patient: I haue ſpoke nor counſelled any thing but what I haue done my ſelfe; and I haue done nothing, but that which is warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the word of God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I hope the word of God doth ſhewmen their duties to wiues, as well as the wiues toward their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>It is ſo: but firſt wee muſt ſhew the one, before we can doe the other.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You ſhould haue begun with the men firſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>It might haply haue bene ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what tedious, and women moſtly are ſo fickle, and wil find themſelues ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things to doe, &amp; are ſo ſoone weary of hearing and reading any good thing, that they would ſcarce ſtay to heare the beginning of their dutie; therefore I thought beſt to begin with them firſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Truſt me, you are a ſmall friend to your owne ſexe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>More then you are to your owne ſelfe; for you are ignorant and careleſſe of that good, which you might haue by your husband, if you would be louing
<pb facs="tcp:7282:26"/> and ſubmiſſiue to him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tell not mee of the good, which I may haue by my ſubmiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; for this is the truth of it, I care not though he heard me: I neuer meane to haue my necke brought vnder his girdle, but I will rather make him buckle &amp; bend vnto me, or elſe he ſhall haue an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet life.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>It is true indeed, that many ſuch as you are wil haue their husbands bend and crouch vnto them. But how ſeemly or warrantable this is, let euery one iudge. It is neither for the womans cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit nor profit, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtreame runs with violence this way. What a horrible ſinne is it, that the woman ſhould vſurpe the mans authority, &amp; the poore man dares not do any thing, but what his wife wil? and as ſhe ſaith ſo it muſt bee, or elſe the houſe will not hold her, neither will ſhe looke vpon him without lumping and lowring; &amp; if any deſcribe the vglines of her countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the time of her anger, ſhe will ſcarce be friends with them. Oh therfore, Oh therefore, that theſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterly dames would but glaſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that they might ſee their rugged
<pb facs="tcp:7282:27"/> browes, their fiery eyes, pouching mouthes, their blacke and poyſoned tonges, which vtter horrible blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies both againſt God and men, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially againſt their husbands, whom they ſhould loue moſt dearely. So heere is the cauſe why many men thinke it their greateſt wiſdome to poſſeſſe their ſoules in patience, and to paſſe by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny grieuances in our ſexe. Onely this is the refuge of thoſe that are godly, to comfort themſelues in the Lord their God. Therefore well (ſaith <hi>Salmon) It is better to liue in the wilderneſſe with a din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of greene hearbes, then to haue a ſtalled oxe, or to liue in a wide houſe with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious woman.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I will be ſworne, if there were but thrée or foure moe here; if they were of my mind, wee would teach you how to defame &amp; ſhame vs on this manner.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>You defame and ſhame your ſelues, I onely ſhew, what ſhrewes are: and thoſe that will neither be ruled by God nor their husbands: as he that tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth not pitch ſhall not be defiled, ſo ſhe that is not of this ſtocke and linage,
<pb facs="tcp:7282:27"/> is not blamed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Let her alone good</hi> Eulaly, <hi>and tel me how did you after your husband was in bed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eulal.</speaker>
                  <p>When his ſtomack was emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied, and he come to himſelfe, when he was not ſtirred in his affections, nor troubled with other actions, but he and I alone, either in bed, or in ſome conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient place, I would gently admoniſh him, or rather intreat him, that he would haue a care of the health of his body, &amp; to auoid that ſin, to bee ouercome with drinck; telling him of ſuch young men, yea gallant gentlemen as he knew, who got ſurfets by ſo ouercharging their ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks: alſo with weeping eies I would intreat him, to haue a care of his eſtate and credit, children and ſeruants, leſt the one ſhould be vndone by his ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their portions, and the other by following his vnſeemely courſe of life. This was the manner of my proceeding with him, ſeaſoning my ſpeeches in the beſt manner, that they might not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſted but digeſted of him. Alſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times I was wont to vſe a preface, and make him promiſe mee, that hee would
<pb facs="tcp:7282:28"/> haue patience with me, if I a ſimple wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhould put him in minde of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that might tend to his credit or welfare any way; &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I had told him my mind, I would breake off that talke, and fall into ſome other more delightful to him. For goſſip <hi>Xantip,</hi> I may ſay to you, that this is the weakenes of vs wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that when wee haue begunne to ſpeake, wee are ſo talkatiue and full of words, that wee wot not when to leaue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is the pleaſure of men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſo to ſay of vs, who haue no better ſport, then to ſpeake of, and report our infirmities: but ſay on I pray you.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>I had alſo a ſpeciall care of this, that I would not find fault with my husband for any thing, in any bodies preſence, nor complaine of him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. A matter is ſoone amended, that is but betweene two, and not blazed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. But if the matter bee of ſuch a nature, that it cannot well be holpen by the wiues counſell, it is a ſeemelier courſe that the wife make complaint to her husbands parents, or ſome of his kindred, rather then to her owne; and alſo that ſhe moderate her complaint &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:7282:28"/> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per her ſpeech ſo, that ſhe may ſeeme not to hate her husbands perſon, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his ill conditions. Neither let her blab out all; that ſo, when her husband comes to heare of it by his friends, that ſhe hath ſpoken of his faultes with the leaſt, he may be forced to acknowledge his wiues courteſie, and kind dealing, &amp; to ſay as <hi>Saul</hi> did of <hi>Dauid: She is more righteous then I.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>She had neede be an Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick, and brought vp in their ſchooles and Vniuerſitie, that ſhould ſkill to do this as you haue ſet downe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By this meanes we ſhall draw our husbands to ſhew vs the like kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>There are ſome huſbands, whom no gentle intreaty will doe any good.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Truely I thinke, there are few or none ſuch: but ſay there be; firſt of al, as I haue ſaid before, the husband muſt be borne, endured, and dwelled with, though neuer ſo wretched and wicked, euen a diuell incarnate. Therefore it is farre better to beare with one like our ſelues, or that may bee bettered by our
<pb facs="tcp:7282:29"/> courteous carriage, then one, that will be worſe euery day then other, by our ouerthwart &amp; crabbed behauiour. Come on <hi>Margerie,</hi> what will you ſay, if I tell you of ſome husbands, that haue refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med their wiues on this wiſe by their gentle carriage. If they doe it, how much more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is it meet, that we ſhould do the ſame to our husbands?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If you can tell vs of a truth of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch, I ſay they are rare ſwans, and ſuch huſbands are hard to come by.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why, there are many ſuch géeſe as you are, will not bee ruled by them, but continually will bee gagling at them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>Shee hath ſuch a ſwanne her ſelfe; if ſhe had eyes to ſe him, or grace to make vſe of him: I would I had ſuch another; if I had, I would thinke I had a rare Iewell.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I am acquainted with ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, who is both a learned and a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man, and of an excellent good cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage. He married a young maid about</hi> 17. <hi>yeares old, brought vp continually in the country; as noble men you know haue a kind of felicity to dwell in the
<pb facs="tcp:7282:29"/> country, that they may there hunt and hauke. He would make choiſe of a plaine and homely wench, to the intent he might better bring her to his bow. He began to teach her to reade, and to plaie on inſtruments, &amp; by little and little to accuſtome her to make relation of ſome points deliuered in the Sermon, and to traine her vp in other matters, which were commendable &amp; profitable. Now becauſe theſe were ſtrange and vncouth to the rude young woman, which had liued quitely in her mothers kitchin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men and maid ſeruants, ſhe grew ſoone weary of them, and would not obey her husband (as you</hi> Margery <hi>wil not:) and when her husband vrged her to them, ſhee would like a child, put fingar in the eye, and ſometimes ſhe would throw her ſelfe vpon the cold ground, and beate her head againſt it, as if ſhee would haue beaten out her braines. Shee continued this courſe a good while; her husband very wiſely winkt at it, and kept in his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. On a day he willed his wife for recreations ſake, to walke with him, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the country to her father. Oh ſhee
<pb facs="tcp:7282:30"/> was in heauen when ſhe heard of that, &amp; went with al her heart with him to her fathers houſe. Being come thither, he left his wife talking with her mother &amp; ſiſters, himſelfe went into the fields a hunting with his father in law; &amp; being there and no body by, he told his father in law, how he hoped, that he had happened on a comfortable companion to haue paſt his life withall; but now he perceiued, that he had one alwaies pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and complaining, and pittifully ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king on, and that hée could not helpe it, with whatſoeuer he could ſay: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he prayed his father to play the Phyſition, and to cure his daughters malady. Her father made him this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere: Son ſaith he, once in the Church I deliuered my daughter to you: if ſhe will not be ruled by your counſell, vſe your authority. Then the young man, thus replied: Father I know very wel, what I may do by my place and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; but I had rather ſhee might bee brought into order by your ſkill, and authority, then to vſe the extreme re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy of Stafford law. Vpon that his father promiſed him to do whathe could
<pb facs="tcp:7282:30"/> to cure and phyſicke his daughters croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and peruerſe diſpoſition. Within a day or two therefore he pickt out a fit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity both of time &amp; place to deale alone with his daughter. Calling her to him aſide, and compoſing his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in a graue and grim manner, and ſolemne ſort, he beganne to ſhew her, what a hard fauoured woman ſhe was, and of no louely qualities, and how he was oft afraid, leaſt hee ſhould neuer haue beſtowed her in marriage: and yet ſaith hee, through the great care that I haue had for thee, I haue procured thee ſuch an huſband, as the moſt courteous and beautifull damſell that is, could not deſire a better. To be briefe, the fathers ſpéech grew ſo hot, that hee could ſcarce hold his hands. The young woman moued partly with feare, and partly with the truth of that her father told her, fell downe at his feet, praying him to forgiue her, and promiſing euer after to be mindfull of her dutie. Her father forgaue her, and ſaid further, that hee would ſhew himſelfe a right father, if ſhe would doe as ſhe promiſed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>And what followed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7282:31"/>
                  <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The young woman going from her father, returned to her chamber, finds her huſband all alone, fals vpon her knees, &amp; cried: O huſband, vnwiſe as I was, I haue not hitherto knowne you nor my ſelfe: hereafter you ſhall ſée me become a new woman: only good huſband forgiue and forget my former diſobedience. This vnexpected humble ſpéech of his wife, hée welcomed with a kiſſe, and promiſed her all things, if ſhée would ſtill continue in this minde.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, but did ſhe ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes to her dying day; neither was there any ſeruice ſo baſe, which ſhée would not willingly vndergoe at her huſbands pleaſure, howſoeuer</hi> Margery <hi>it may be, you would haue done it at your leaſure. And there grew euery day ſuch great loue betwixt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that within few yeares ſhe would often in company reioyce &amp; bleſſe God that ſhee was mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with ſuch a huſband, whom if ſhée had not maried, ſhe thought there ſhould not haue bene a more miſerable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vnder the Sunne.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>Such men as theſe are as rare as white crowes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7282:31"/>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yet you haue ſuch an one.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>The greater ſhall her iudgment be, except ſhe repent: for there are few women in the country, I can tell you, that haue ſuch a religious husband, who ſeeketh by all meanes her ſaluation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Haue you no mo ſuch exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, that I haue, and one e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciall one, which I hope will pleaſe <hi>Margery,</hi> it being much in the comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of a woman, as the other was of a man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I pray you let vs heare it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>There was a neighbour of ours, a very honeſt man, but ſomewhat of a haſtie nature, and of a waſpiſh &amp; tetchy diſpoſition: on a day he beate his wife, a woman, by common report, of ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar good carriage, and excellent behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, ſuch an one as <hi>Abigail,</hi> being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well beloued of all her neighbours. Being beaten &amp; abuſed of her husband, ſhe betakes her ſelfe into her ſecret clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, and there ſhee ſits ſighing and ſob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, ſo eaſing her heart, and diſgeſting her griefe. Soone after vpon occaſion her husband went into that roome, and finding his wife wofully weeping, ſaies
<pb facs="tcp:7282:32"/> to her: Why ſitteſt thou here fighing &amp; ſobbing, and crying, like a child? Shee then thus prudently and patiently an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered: Husband, ſaid ſhee, is it not better to doe thus, here to bewaile my griefe where no body heares nor ſees, then to runne and cry out in the ſtreetes, and to exclaime on you, as others do on their husbands? By this wiſe and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſpeech of his wife, the ſtout heart of her husband was broken: hee gaue her his right hand, and promiſed that hee would neuer touch her againe in any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill manner; neither did he.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I haue brought my huſband to that paſſe too, but yet another way then ſhe did.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>But I thinke you cannot yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why, what would you haue me to do?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>O <hi>Xantip,</hi> how oft haue I told thee how thou ſhouldſt behaue thy ſelfe to thy husband? I perceiue thou haſt a bad memory, or at leaſt, ſmall liſt to learne, ſith ſo ſoone thou forgetteſt thy duty. Wel, once more I wil tel thee. Firſt you muſt put vp all iniury at his hands.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7282:32"/>
                  <speaker>Marg.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yea, ſo one might ſoone bée made a foole &amp; a foot-ſtoole: I would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do him two for one.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Hold you your tongue <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery,</hi> I ſpeake not to you but to <hi>Xantip.</hi> Then <hi>Xantip</hi> you muſt labour to win his good will by doing all duties with chearefulneſſe, and louing kindneſſe: ſo ſhal you at laſt ouercome him, or at leaſt you ſhall haue him in a farre better tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per then he is in at this preſent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Alas woman, he is farre fier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer then he was before: I feare me, no gentleneſſe will preuaile with him.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Feare not woman, there is no wild beaſt ſo ſauage, but by gentle hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it may be tamed: be not then hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of a man; do but put in practiſe &amp; vre my aduice for a few moneths, and then blame me, if you find not my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell to doe you good. There are ſome ſmal faults which you muſt winke at; &amp; take heede that you giue no occaſion of contention, and thinke no ſcorne to be ſeruiceable in thoſe things which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come you. There are ſome women that will be euer frumping or whining, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or neuer vſing any amiable beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour
<pb facs="tcp:7282:33"/> toward their husbands, which is a ſigne that they haue not the loue of God ſhed abroad in their hearts. For if they had, it would cauſe them to loue their husbands vnſpeakeably.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Indéed goſſip, I muſt tell you plainly, I cannot ſhew that loue to my huſband that I ſhould, and ſome do to theirs, he is ſo croſſe to me, and euery way ſo vntoward.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>But I hope it would bee for your good, if hee would leaue his bad quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: ſuppoſe when you are angry with your husband, that then you could by the art of <hi>Circes</hi> transforme your huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band into a ſwine, or a Beare, or any ſuch like beaſt, would you not do it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I know I ſhould not: but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I would yea or no, its hard to ſay.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>What, had you rather haue a ſwine or a Beare to your hushand then a man?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You doe not heare me ſay ſo; I trow, no.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Go to then, what if you could make him of a wine-bibber, a ſober per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; of a ding-thrift a good husband; of a ſlothfull, a painefull perſon; of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane
<pb facs="tcp:7282:33"/> creature, a religious and zealous Chriſtian, would you not do it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>There is a queſtion indeede. Yes, with all my heart would I: but how ſhould I do it?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Xantip, Xantip,</hi> thou art like vnto thoſe women which the Apoſtle ſpeakes of, that are alwaies learning, and are neuer taught: ſo thou art alwaies asking how ſhal I do this and that, and yet thou remaineſt ſtill ignorant: and wilt thou know why thou art ſo ignorant ſtill, and forgetfull?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xan.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes, with a good will.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>It is becauſe you do not practiſe that which is taught you. I ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to you, that you muſt adorne the Goſpell of Chriſt by your holy conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. Now if you be a Chriſtian, as I thought you were, &amp; ſuppoſe you think no leſſe of your ſelfe; of you the Apoſtle askes this queſtion: What knoweſt thou ô wife, whether thou ſhalt win thy huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band? meaning, by thy holy example, gracious words &amp; counſell, praiers and patience, your conference and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Now if by any meanes you can win your husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, what a rich crowne of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:7282:34"/> ſhall you obtaine? what vnſpeakea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ioy and comfort ſhall you haue both in this life, and in the life to come? Set not your eies ſo much vpon his ill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions: for that makes them ſeeme grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then they be; and to twit him with them, is not the way to bring him to goodneſſe, but to make him worſe. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you were maried to him, you ſhold haue conſidered what his ill qualities were: for it behoues a woman not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to chuſe a husband by her eies, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by her eares, and by experience of his qualities; neither is it a time after once they be maried, of complaining &amp; accuſing, but of curing their bad huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What woman knew you euer, that choſe her huſband with her eares?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>She chuſes a husband with her eies, that reſpects nothing but his viſage and perſonage: and ſhe chuſeth him by her eares, that warily &amp; wiſely weighes what the world, eſpecially the beſt ſort, ſay of him; and ſhe chuſeth him by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, who trieth his loue and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This is good counſell, but
<pb facs="tcp:7282:34"/> it is all too late.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>But it is not too late to labour the reformation of your husband; and yet it ſhall be in very good time, if you can profite your husband. For the way to good manners is neuer too late; and you both ſhall finde a double comfort of it, if your husband ſhal haue any children by you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I haue one already.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>When, I pray you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A pretty while agoe?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>How many moneths ſince?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Welnéere ſeuen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>How can that bee? Is it poſſible that you ſhould haue a child in three moneths?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tuſh, it is longer.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>It is not a day longer, if you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne your reckoning from the mariage day.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yea, but we had conference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Like inough; but I hope chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are not gotten with conference. Is this you that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaine of your husband ſo much? I perceiue one houſe is better troubled with you then two. I feare I
<pb facs="tcp:7282:35"/> haue beſtowed all my labour in vaine vpon you? what thinke you will our neighbour <hi>Abigail</hi> ſay, when ſhe heares of this? it will grieue her not a little.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We were ſure together before.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>The ſin is ſomething the leſſe, but yet except it be repented of, and that from the heart, God will puniſh you both for it; and therefore looke to it, &amp; lament it, as alſo all other your miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanors. What is it, a boy?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes, a goodly lad, God bleſſe it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>You muſt haue a ſpeciall care to bring him vp in the feare of the Lord; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe make your reckoning that hee will be a great croſſe to you both: but if you wil catechiſe him now from his cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, &amp; ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually, no doubt but he wil be a meanes to ſet you at one, if that you will but incline a little to your husbands minde. I pray you tell me, what do other men ſay of your husband, your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and thoſe that haue dealing with him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They commend him out of all cry for a courteous, liberall, and friendly man.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>This makes me hope that he will
<pb facs="tcp:7282:35"/> proue ſuch an one as we would haue him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But I am ſure that I find him not ſuch an one to me, whatſoeuer they ſay.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea but do you ſhew your ſelfe ſuch an one towards him, as I haue coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled you; and if he proue not ſuch an one in time as I ſaid, call me <hi>Eulalie</hi> no longer, but <hi>Pſeudolalie,</hi> or lyer. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer remember, that yet he is but a yong man, not, as I thinke, aboue foure and twenty yeares old; alas poore ſoule, he knowes not yet what belongs to a huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band or houſekeeping. You muſt not thinke to bee ſeparated from him, as a great many do, if ſo bee they cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree vpon euery thing, then ſtraight no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſeparation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God forgiue me, I haue often wiſhed it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>But repent of that; and if euer it come into your minde, conſider with your ſelfe how friuolous a thing it is for a woman to be diuorced from her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, ſith ſo many inconueniences fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of it. Againe, thinke with your ſelfe, that it is the crowne and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
<pb facs="tcp:7282:36"/> of a matron to be obedient to her husband, as hath bene ſaid; yea, that it is a thing ordained in nature, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed by God, that the woman ſhould wholly depend vpon the man, &amp; haue him as her head. Alſo remember the pretty little boy, the fruit of your wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be; what would you doe with him, if you went away? would you carry him with you? then you ſhould depriue your huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of his right: would you leaue him with your husband? then you ſhall depriue your ſelfe of part of your ſelfe. Laſtly, tell me, haue you any that beare you ill will?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes, I haue a ſtep-mother, &amp; mother in law like her: for they hate me ſo much, that I thinke they could wiſh I were at the Diuell.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Then remember them alſo. For what could you do to make them reioice more, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if they ſhould ſee you liue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone like a widow; nay worſe then a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow: for thoſe may mary againe, but ſo could not you, but muſt liue rather like an harlot that is ſeparated for adultery.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I muſt néeds ſay your counſell is good, but I cannot abide to be thus
<pb facs="tcp:7282:36"/> vexed euery day.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>But thinke with your ſelfe what great labour you tooke before you could teach this parrot to pronounce ſome words.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It was a long time indéede.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>And doth it ſeeme irkſome and tedious vnto you to take ſome paines to make your husband a good man? You are not the woman I tooke you for: for I alwaies thought that you would haue refuſed nothing that might be profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to both your ſoules and bodies, and that you might paſſe your daies in peace &amp; pleaſure. You haue heard how great paines men take to breake their horſes, and what curious meanes and deuices they vſe to tame Lonys, Bulles, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lephants, and ſhall we thinke much to take a little paines to haue good huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What ſhall I doe?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly, it grieues me to heare you. This is the foot of your ſong com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly: What ſhall I do? Why this do. Be carefull that your houſe be neate and cleanly, that there may bee nothing to driue your husband out of doores. Be
<pb facs="tcp:7282:37"/> gentle, louing and kinde to him: be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies mindfull of that reuerence which is due to him. Be not lumpiſh, nor yet to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>boyiſh: be not ſluttiſh, nor yet gariſh in your apparell: let your meate be well dreſſed, and in due ſeaſon: know your husbands tooth: let him haue that which will delight his palate: ſhew your ſelfe gentle and affable to his friends, bidde them often to your houſe, and ſee with chearfulnes all be ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſome. When your husband is merry, be not you ſad: &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is melancholy, be not you merry: for contraries wil not agree together. Make his bed ſoft, &amp; ſee that euery thing which is good bee prouided for him. By this meanes you ſhall haue him keepe home, and ſo ſaue idle expences: for thus will he thinke with himſelfe at length. Good Lord, what meane I? what a foole am I that liue ranging abroad with loſſe of my goods and good name, by keeping drabbe, and drunken company, when I haue ſuch a good and louing wife at home, which takes more pleaſure in me, then this flattering harlot? why then, much more ſhould I bee delightfull to her, if I would quite leaue theſe truls,
<pb facs="tcp:7282:37"/> and ſwilling company. Well, I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue with my ſelfe henceforth to leaue this filthy and beaſtly courſe of life.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doe you thinke that I ſhall preuaile?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>You are very incredulous, and a woman of ſmall hope: you would ill do I perceiue as a certaine graue matron did, which I had thought to haue told you of before, but I let it then paſſe, becauſe I would not bee tedious vnto you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I pray tell me, what ſhee did.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>You are maruellous deſirous of nouelties, and inquiſitiue to know: it were an excellent thing in you, if you were as readie to practiſe what you know, and to follow the good examples you heare of.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Well, I hope I ſhall doe it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>I will briefly ſhew you the ſame: not that I would haue you to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low her ſteppes, but learne wiſedome from her policie. There was an anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Gentleman, who gaue himſelfe to hunting, and as he was an hunting, hee light vpon a yong maid, a poore woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s daughter. For loue of her, hee would
<pb facs="tcp:7282:38"/> leaue his owne houſe, and frequent that. His wife ſuſpecting ſome ſuch matter, watched him one time whither he went, and ſeeing him goe to a poore cottage, thither ſhe went one day, when he was away, and got out of them what he did there, how he lay; ſhe could ſee nothing there but bare ſtone-wals, &amp; meere po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty. Shee goes home in haſt, and makes no leſſe ſpeed againe, bringing with her a handſome bed, &amp; good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, with ſiluer plate, and alſo gaue them mony, willing them, if he came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more, to make more of him and giue him better entertainment; not telling them all this wile, that ſhe was his wife, but made ſemblance as though ſhe were his ſiſter. Soone after ſhee was gone, comes her husband priuily, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what was done; and ſeeing the houſe richly furniſhed, his diet more dainty, and greater plenty of it then ordinary, he asked them whence they had all this furniture and prouiſion. They told him, that a graue matron a kinſwoman of his brought it them, and charged them at her departure, to giue him better atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance and entertainment. By and by
<pb facs="tcp:7282:38"/> his heart ſmote him, and told him, that it was his wife: he goes home in all haſt asking her, whether ſhe had ben in ſuch a place; ſhee tels him yea; then he asked her, what ſhe meant by it, to carrie bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and ſuch a deale of good plate and prouiſion thither. O husband ſaith ſhe, you haue bene vſed euer ſince I knew you, to a better diet and lodging, then I ſee any there; for you haue there but bad entertainment. Therefore I thought it my dutie, ſith it was your pleaſure vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what occaſion I know not, often to reſort thither, that you ſhould haue bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter prouiſion when you came, then they could affoord you. Now marke the iſſue, when the man ſaw the tender loue and care of his wife, he neuer ſtole out after, but continually kept her company at home. Alſo I could make rehearſall of another, if I thought it expedient, which inuited home her husbands paramour; and if hee ſupped abroad with her, would ſend them ſome one dainty diſh or other, and by this meanes win their husbands loue wholy to themſelues. But howſoeuer this fell out at ſometime, yet it is not lawfull to take the ſame courſe,
<pb facs="tcp:7282:39"/> though wee were in hope, our attempt ſhould haue ſucceſſe; for wee muſt not doe euill, that good may come of it. But to this end I haue alledged theſe two laſt, that if women haue won their husbands, which were lincked to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots; then much more may Chriſtian women by their louely and holy carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, be in hope to win them, which hate ſuch ſtrumpets, And thou <hi>Xantip,</hi> that ſaieſt thy husband haunteth harlots, this is my counſel to thee, to make much of him; not becauſe he doth that wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or to fleſh him in his luſt, but that therby thou maiſt reclaime him from it: but in no caſe countenance thou his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I purpoſe to practiſe your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Looke on me; I promiſe you, if you practiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as you haue often ſaid, you ſhall finde me a friend indeed, and I will goe to your husband, and get <hi>Abigail,</hi> that can giue beter counſel then I, to goe with me; and wee will tell him throughly of his duty, yea and that in ſuch a manner, as I make no doubt, but hee ſhall accept of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7282:39"/>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I commend your courſe. But take heede hee ſmell vs not out; for if he know, that I haue made his faults knowne to you, he will be ſo out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious, as though he would bring hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth together, and take on with mee like a madde man, and bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Feare not, wee will bring the matter ſo cunningly about, &amp; fetch him ſo finely ouer, that I make no doubt, but that we will draw out of himſelfe, what broyles haue bene betwixt you; and when wee haue drawne out all his corruptions as cleane as wine out of a veſſell, then will wee put into him the heauenly liquor of holy doctrine, and tell him how hee is to demeane himſelfe towards you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt proſper our enterpriſes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>We may bee ſure that hee will giue vs good ſucceſſe, if wee doe not croſſe our ſelues. So fare you well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God ſpéede neighbour</hi> Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ezer, <hi>how haue you done a long time?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>Welcome neighbours, wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: how do you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tell vs I pray you, how doth
<pb facs="tcp:7282:40"/> your wife?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>Euen like a ſhrew, for any thing I know.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If I may be ſo bold as ſpeaks, it is better to be a ſheepe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>I giue you my word goſſip, my wife is not a ſheep, nay, I pray God ſhee proue not a wolfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It pleaſes men many times to ſpeak their pleaſures of their wiues, though they be neuer ſo kind to them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>Kind? my wife is ſo kind, that Ile warrant her ſhee will neuer kill mee with kindneſſe, for hers is contrary to nature and womanniſhnes; for I thinke there is not a verier ſhrew, and horribler ſcold liuing vpon the earth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yea but neighbour, I pray you giue me liue, you know that men are ſometimes haſty, and will moue their wiues to ſpeake.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>Speake, ſay you? As the ſaying is, there is a difference betweene ſtaring and ſtarke madde; ſo may I ſay, there is a difference betweene ſpeaking &amp; ſcol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. For I will tell you neighbours, I was but forth the other night ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what late, with a friend or two of mine;
<pb facs="tcp:7282:40"/> but good Lord, when I came home, what a life ſhee kept? I had no ſooner put my head within doores, but ſhee gaue mee ſuch a terrible looke, and vttered ſuch an horrible voice, that I thought verily that ſhe would haue flowne in my face, and haue ſcratched out mine eyes; vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring theſe ſpeeches, Where the poxe haue you bene all this while? Is not this a fine time to come home at. You are welcome from your whores with a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine; a vengeance light vpon you, and the deuill in hell fetch you: I would you might breake your neck one night, that I might be ridde of you ſome way or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Is it poſſible, that ſhe ſhould be ſuch a terrible woman?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>If you did but heare her ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, neighbours, you would bleſſe your ſelues; for I think in my conſcience that ſhe is as terrible as a Lyon, as ſubtil as a ſerpent, and as wicked as the diuell himſelfe; for what with her ſcolding, what with her ſwearing, and with her tumults and burſtling vp and downe, you would thinke the very houſe would fall vpon our heads.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7282:41"/>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O the vnſpeakeable patience and mercie of our God, that hee ſuffers ſuch things vnpuniſhed!</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Good neighbour learne to beare with your wiues weakenes &amp; infirmities.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Infirmities? what call you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>The wiues infirmitie toward her husband is, when ſhe cannot put vp wrong at his hands.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Put vp wrong? ſhee will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge two rather, then put vp one. I thinke ſhee would vexe the patienteſt man vpon the earth: ſometimes ſhee moues mee ſo much, that I am readie to beate out her braines.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>God forbid, I am verie much grieued to heare of ſuch bitter contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on berweene man and wife; and ſo, I am ſure, is my neighbour <hi>Eulaly.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I will tell you both but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, how ſhee hath vſed me. If I ſpend but a teaſter or tweluepence, then ſhee railes vpon me, as if I were her pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice boy, that had ſtolne it from her: or if I will not buy her this toy, or that new-fangle, this dainty morſell or that; ſhee takes on like a mad woman, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:7282:41"/> that ſuch a woman can haue this, &amp; that for a word, and why may not ſhée, as well haue the ſame? And if I be but foorth a little, why then ſhee will raile vpon mee, as if I were her ſlaue, yea a diuell incarnate: though many times ſhee is foorth halfe a day, yea a whole day together, ſhee thinkes I muſt ſay nothing; if I doe, it ſhall bee ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, &amp; ten times more ſhall be made of it, then either I ſaid or thought. When ſhe comes in, if I doe but ſay in all gentle manner:</hi> Xantip, <hi>or wife, where haſt thou bene? ſtraight ſhe will ſnappe me vp with this anſwere, Why what care you? or what haue to doe? muſt I make you accounts? (marry muffe:) can I go no whither but you muſt know it? I will aſke you leaue, when you are dead, &amp;c. Or if I aſke her, why didſt thou ſtaie ſo long? ſhee will anſwere, If I had knowne my ſtaying would haue angred you, I would not haue come yet, I will goe &amp; come when I liſt for all you. If I ſpeake her faire, ſhe thinkes I flatter her, and will begin to frump and frowne: if I threaten, then ſhe will bend her fiſts, and tell mée
<pb facs="tcp:7282:42"/> to my face, that I ſhall haue as good or worſe then I bring; and will ſtand da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and challenging mee for the blood in my belly, &amp;c. What man thinke you can endure ſuch a woman?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed if al theſe things be true, which you haue ſaid, ſhee hath bene much to blame; but I hope neighbour that ſhe wil become now a new woman, if that you would but a little beare with her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>She is nought, ſtarke nought, neuer ſpeake for her: I haue forborne her too much and too long, &amp; I perceiue that if I giue her an inch, ſhee will take an ell.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>O neighbour, good neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, now be patient, and doe but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how wee deale with God, and yet he waiteth with patience, looking if at any time wee will turne vnto him: and though we be obſtinate ſtill, yet he offers himſelfe vnto vs in loue, whereas long ago iuſtly he might haue deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vs in the middeſt of our ſinnes for euer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I promiſe you</hi> Abigail, <hi>you ſay true: if God indeed were not very
<pb facs="tcp:7282:42"/> patient &amp; exceeding mercifull, it would be wrong with vs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>Therefore the long patience and goodneſſe of God, ought to leade vs to repentance, and to deale fauourably and in tender compaſſion one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You ſay true, it ſhould doe ſo indeed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, and it muſt doe ſo too, if we will be the Lords ſeruants, as it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Let your patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t mind be knowne vnto all men, the Lord is at hand. Now if this one leſſon were deepely written in our heartes by the holy Ghoſt, wee would not be ſo readie to take reuenge one vpon another, as we doe, neither ſhould ſuch bitter and poyſonful ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches proceed from vs, as commonly do; neither would wee put the euill day far from vs, as the moſt doe: but we would with ſpeed depart from iniquity, and waite diligently and continually for the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Beleeue mée, beléeue mée, I would my</hi> Xantip <hi>were here, to heare you, I hope your good words will do her good.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7282:43"/>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas ſir, we are but ſimple wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, little able to doe either you or her that good, which you might haue rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped by the word of God preached: but yet if it pleaſe you to giue vs leaue, wee will ſhew our mindes, what a comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing it is for man and wife to liue together in loue and charity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Indeed, I thinke no two wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the towne, no nor in the whole country, can ſhew it better then you, becauſe you know what it is by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>Wee thanke God, wee both haue experience of it to our comforts, and ſo would we, that you had, with the loſſe of the beſt horſe or cow, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of vs haue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I thanke you both, and I had rather then the beſt gelding in my ſtable with twenty pound vpon his backe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>Seeing then that peace betweene man and wife is ſo comfortable, &amp; you would ſo gladly enioy it with ſo great loſſe; will you bee content to hearken, and bee thankefull to God, if that wee ſhew you a direct way, how you and your wife might agree together, as
<pb facs="tcp:7282:43"/> long as you ſhall liue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Be contented, ſay you? yea &amp; be glad of the time that euer you ſet footing ouer my threſhold. I haue had ſo much vnquietneſſe alreadie, that me thinkes a little peace, would be as a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle paradice to my ſoule; but yet if my wife did know, that I deſired and labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for peace, ſhée would be the further off it, except God wrought aboue ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary in her.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>We are but women, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſomething baſhfull, as it beſeemes vs, to ſpeake vnto you beeing a man, of theſe matters; yet vnder leaue and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, we will do our good wil to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare thoſe things which wee haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and partly know by experience.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You are both ancient, and I am but young, and my wife alſo; and therefore I would you could direct and tell vs a way how to liue quietly.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>Firſt of all, before you can loue one another as you ought, you muſt labour for the loue of God, which muſt bee ſhed abroad in your heartes, the which loue, will cauſe you to loue one another.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7282:44"/>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I hope wee haue the loue of God already, otherwiſe I am of the minde, that hee would either puniſh vs, or elſe take his bleſſings from vs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>Doe you not thinke this a great puniſhment, that you cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree? Truly I may ſafely ſay, that it is a puniſhment both to your bodies and ſoules.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I confeſſe indeed that it is a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, but yet I hope that God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth many men &amp; women, that yet fall out betwixt themſelues.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>Surely if there bee continuall ſtrife, it is an euident ſigne, that the Lord loueth not the one of them, if not both.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But how ſhould wee know whom it is that the Lord doth not loue?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>They which are the cauſe of the continuing and breeding of the broiles.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That is my</hi> Xantip.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>But who will you be iudged by?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By God and the country.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, God iudgeth the heart: &amp; for your ſelfe we haue heard that you haue a good report among your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; therefore I haue the better hope
<pb facs="tcp:7282:44"/> of you: and therefore I pray you let me aske you one queſtion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aſke me two if you will, I will tell you if I can, I like your talke ſo well.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>What thinke you is the loue of God to his children?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That is too hard a queſtion for me to anſwer, I doe not profeſſe my ſelfe a Diuine.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>But euery Chriſtian ought to be a Diuine, eſpecially in ſuch principles as the loue of God is, without which none poſſible can be ſaued in this life, nor in the life to come.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I do beleeue verily that whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the Lord loues not, them hee hates, and whomſoeuer he hates, vpon them abides his wrath and heauy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, till hee beſtow vpon them his loue; and therefore I pray you, if you can, ſhew me what the loue of God is, and I will gladly heare you.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>The ſingular loue of God vnto his elect is that whereby he loueth them in himſelfe, and hath adopted them in his ſonne Chriſt, before the foundations of the world; and hereto pertaines pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination
<pb facs="tcp:7282:45"/> vocation, the gift of faith, and of the ſpirit, iuſtification, regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and eternall ſaluation, with what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is good, comfortable and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for them in this life. And here by your patience, it ſhall not bee amiſſe to ſhew likewiſe the loue of Chriſt vnto his Church, becauſe we are to fetch our light from his candle.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I pray you do: for I haue both good leaſure and pleaſure to heare you.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>Our Lord Ieſus Chriſt being in the throne of glory, yea, being the Lord of glory, diſrobed himſelfe, and came downe from heauen, and of God became man for our ſakes, taking our nature vpon him; endured much miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the ſpace of 30 yeares &amp; vpward, was as an exile amongſt his cruell ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, which reproched, buffeted, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed, &amp; perſecuted him vnto death: beſides that, hee ſuffered the wrathfull diſpleaſure of his Father in his ſoule, and the grieuous torments of hell that were due vnto vs, that he might free vs therefrom, as it is written: <hi>The chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our peace was laid vpon him, &amp; by his ſtripes are we healed. Eſay.</hi> 53. Hee was
<pb facs="tcp:7282:45"/> made a curſe for the ſinne of man, that ſo man might in him bee bleſſed. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neighbour how ought theſe things to worke vpon our conſciences, and to force euery one of vs particularly to ſay: O miſerable wretch that I am, that for my ſinne my Sauiour ſhould ſuffer ſuch horrible puniſhment? ô ſweet Sauiour, how am I bound to praiſe and thanke thee? Who am I that thou ſhouldeſt thinke, much leſſe looke on me, or doe any thing for me, ſeeing that I haue ſo many waies offended thee? But this is thy mercy, yea thine incomprehenſible and vnſpeakeable loue, that thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not onely free me from death and damnation, but bring me to life and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, euen to a better eſtate then <hi>Adam</hi> was in before his fall. O the admirable mercy of God, and the incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble loue of Chriſt, how am I bound vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee? What thankes and praiſe is due vnto thy maieſty for theſe vnſpeakea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bleſſings? for that thou haſt not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly freed me from eternal miſery, but haſt brought me vnto euerlaſting happines, and made me one with thee, as thou art one with thy Father, that I might bee
<pb facs="tcp:7282:46"/> glorified in thee, as thou art in him; &amp; to this end thou haſt made me bone of thy bone, and fleſh of thy fleſh, ſo that thou art become wholly mine, with all things that belong to thee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O good neighbour conſider of this vnſpeakeable loue of God and his Son Chriſt towards his whole Church in generall, and to euery one of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in particular, how that the Lord of his free grace hath wrought in vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and faith, and hath ſhed his loue abroad in our hearts, and aſſured vs of the frée pardon of all our ſinnes, and of his euerlaſting loue and fauour in his Sonne Chriſt Ieſus our Lord: and hath made vs one with himſelfe, &amp; his Sonne, &amp; partakers of his diuine nature, and hath filled our hearts with vnſpeakeable comfort and ioy of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, which wee deſired ſo much in the daies of our affliction. And further, hath giuen vnto vs his Spirit, which is the earneſt pennie of our euerlaſting happineſſe; and which doth ſanctifie vs daily more and more, and ſtrengthen vs to euery good worke; and hath promiſed that no good thing ſhall be wanting vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:7282:46"/> vs, if we will be obedient vnto him. How ought theſe things to cauſe vs to loue God againe, and for his ſake to loue one another? ſeeing that he of his méere mercy hath made vs partakers of ſuch happineſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>They are happy indeede that haue all theſe things beſtowed vpon them which you haue ſpoken of.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Euery true Chriſtian is in ſuch a happy eſtate before they can find ſound comfort vnto their ſoules, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can performe any duty plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vnto God, or before they can loue their wiues as they ought.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>Then there are but few that loue their wiues as they ought.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is true indéed, and more is the pitty. For ſome loue their wiues for their luſts ſake, ſome for their beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſake, ſome for their riches ſake, ſome for their friends ſake, ſome for natures ſake, &amp; ſome for neceſſities ſake; becauſe they ſée if they ſhould not, it would not ſtand with their quiet, profite, &amp; cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. But take once away the aforeſaid cauſes, &amp; their loue falles to the ground. If it bee for luſt, when that is ſatiſfied,
<pb facs="tcp:7282:47"/> he rather hates the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loues her, as</hi> Ammon <hi>did his ſiſter,</hi> 2. Sam. 13.15. <hi>if for beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; as that vaniſheth, his loue decaieth; if for riches, nature, or friends ſake; as they leſſen, his loue leſſens with them; if it be for neceſſitie, it is counterfaite: or if ſhe winne his loue, as ſome doe, by her faire language, then it turneth as the winde. Finally, if it be for any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward cauſe, or for all the cauſes vnder the cope of heauen, without the loue of God, it will bee vncomfortable, vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and vnſound: but if it be for the loue of God, though for no other cauſe in the earth, it wil be vndefiled, comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, continuall, and increaſe more and more. But all loue elſe whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer that proceedes from the husbande to the wife, and from the wife to the husband, is rebellion againſt God; and the more a man loues his wife, or the wife her husband, the more they ſinne againſt God. Howſoeuer this may ſéeme harſh vnto worldly men, yet that which doth enſue will make it plaine; for the more that both husband and wife loue each other without louing God, the more they will ſeeke to fulfill
<pb facs="tcp:7282:47"/> their fleſhly luſts, though they be neuer ſo much againſt God, and his word. Therfore it behoues euery man to loue his wife with ſuch loue, as Chriſt did his Church.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>What manner of loue was that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It was not fleſhly, but ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, not earthly, but heauenly.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>But muſt he not loue her out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, and prouide ſuch things for her, as are neceſſary, profitable, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, for the preſeruing and cheriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of her body?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes, it is the part and dutie of euery man, chiefly of a Chriſtian ſo to doe, (as I would haue ſhewed you anon) or elſe he ſhall not onely ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her, but againſt God alſo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you now ſhew, how a man muſt firſt ſhew his loue to his wife, and what is the firſt fruit of his loue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the firſt place, hee muſt giue himſelfe vnto God with faſting &amp; prayer, that the Lord would bleſſe his enterpriſes and proceedings; and when he hath humbled himſelfe vnto God he muſt not thinke much to humble him
<pb facs="tcp:7282:48"/> ſelfe to his wife.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>This wil be harſh vnto the moſt men, and they will hardly, or neuer, bee brought vnto it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But if they will be Chriſtian men, they muſt do it, and that for theſe cauſes. Firſt, becauſe it is not hurtfull, but good and profitable not againſt the word, but warrantable and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by it. And laſtly, becauſe Chriſt hath giuen them example ſo to do.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you, if you can, ſhew theſe things more plainly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the firſt, if you looke from the beginning of</hi> Geneſis <hi>to the latter end of the</hi> Apocalypſe, <hi>you ſhall neuer finde it ſpoken againſt, either openly, nor incluſiuely; and therupon I gather, that ſeeing it is profitable, it may bee practiſed in a ciuil and courteous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. And againe, humility is a vertue, and the more eminent place a man is in, the more it doth adorne him, if he be endued with it. And further, though he bee in neuer ſo high a place, hee is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to humble himſelfe to his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; yea and to make himſelfe, as he is a Chriſtian, equall with them of the
<pb facs="tcp:7282:48"/> lower ſort. Now if it bee his dutie to humble himſelfe towards euery one, &amp; to make himſelfe equall with thoſe of the loweſt ſort: then much more to his wife. Againe, they are commanded to honour their wiues as the weaker veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels; that is, as I take it, not onely to beare with their wiues infirmities, but to ſubmit their mindes vnto them in that which is good, &amp; kindly to intreate them in humbleneſſe of minde, and to aduance their credit and good name, and to ſtand in their defence againſt whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer that oppoſe themſelues againſt them. And laſtly, by Chriſts example, they are to be lowly, and humbly to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelues vnto their wiues, as he doth vnto his Church and people.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>How doth Chriſt humbly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit himſelfe vnto his Church and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt doth ſubmit and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble himſelfe vnto his Church and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, both in himſelfe, and by others. His ſubmiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſhewed both by his words, geſture, and actions. By his words, when he louingly intreats her to leaue her corruptions, and to accept of his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:7282:49"/> fauour and kindneſſe, which he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers vnto her as a token of his loue and vnfaigned deſire he hath that ſhe ſhould bee at peace with him; and to the end that he might win her loue, hee makes many gracious and beauteous promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes vnto her; yea, hee beſtowes many rich treaſures vpon her, ſuing &amp; wooing of her, and ſometimes when ſhe turnes her backe vpon him, hee turnes his face to her, ſaying: what ailes my loue, my doue, my vndefiled ſpouſe? when ſhe is ſad, he wil make her ioyful many times, when ſhée frownes, hée will looke vpon her with a chearefull countenance. And againe, he attendeth and waiteth at the gates of her portall, ſaying:</hi> Behold I ſtand at the doore and knocke, open vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, my loue, my doue, and vndefiled. <hi>And moreouer for his Churches ſake, which is his wife, he bended his knées, and humbled himſelfe vnto the earth: yea, vnto death, and that vnto the moſt ſhamefull and horrible death of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe. What baeſneſſe did hee refuſe to honour her? Conſider the reproches and indignities he endured, of the paines &amp; miſeries which hee vnderwent for the
<pb facs="tcp:7282:49"/> loue he bare vnto her, and to winne her vnto him againe; and ſtill how he doth ſend his meſſengers and embaſſadours to entreate his Church in his ſtead to bee reconciled vnto him.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>One would thinke that theſe things ſhould cauſe the heart of man to ſtoop, and to bend his affections vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his wife.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes verily, ſo thinke I too, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle had I thought that any could haue made theſe things ſo plaine.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>If ſo be you thinke theſe things ſo euident, which I a ſimple woman haue opened vnto you: how much more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident then thinke you, ſhould they haue bene, if a godly learned man had had the matter in handling?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Well, ſéeing it is ſo plaine as it is, what is the next courſe that I muſt take, that there may be peace and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall loue betwéene me and my wife?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>After you haue done as I haue ſet downe, and declared your loue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your wife, you then with wiſedome and reuerence, and in a louing manner, muſt ſhew vnto her her miſerable eſtate, which ſhe ſtands in, and the iudgements
<pb facs="tcp:7282:50"/> of God due vnto her for ſinne, that ſo ſhe may be humbled.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But if I ſhould tell my</hi> Xan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tip <hi>of her miſerable eſtate, ſhe would be ſo farre from humbling her ſelfe, that ſhe would rather be ready to fly in my face.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope not ſo. But hearken, I pray you. Men do many times faile in the manner of their directions and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions vnto their wiues, which is the cauſe that they profite no more then they do: for commonly in their anger they will tell their wiues of their faults, and that in ſuch a haſtie and hare-braind ſort as ſpoiles all: or elſe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their wiues are moodie, and troubled in minde; ſo that it is no maruell that they doe more hurt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good. The very heathen would not fight nor reproue in their anger; how much more then ought Chriſtians to waite their oportunities, when they may do the moſt good?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why, but do you hold then that a man may beate his wife when he is quiet?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay. Much leſſe when he is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7282:50"/>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>There was neuer any that hated their owne fleſh, but nouriſhed and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed it. Now the wife is the husbands owne fleſh, as it is written: <hi>They twaine ſhall be one fleſh. Therefore, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yea, but though he beate her, yet he néed not hate her. And againe, hath not the man as much power ouer his wiues body, as the father hath ouer the child: but the father may correct and whip his child for his fault, and yet loue him too. For it is written in the</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs: Hee that corrects not his child, hates him</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>The compariſon is not equall, howſoeuer it bee granted that the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band hath power ouer the wiues body: yet it is not in that manner as the father hath power ouer the childs: he hath po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ouer the wines body for procreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo ſhe hath power ouer his, and both ouer the childs for correction. So by this kinde of reaſoning the wife hath as great prerogatiue ouer the mans bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as the man hath ouer the wiues. For ſo ſaith the Apoſtle: <hi>The man hath not power ouer his owne body, but the wife: nor the wife ouer hers, but her husband.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7282:51"/>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Againe, it is ſaid, that</hi> S. Paul <hi>did beate downe his own body, to bring it vnder, when it would not bee in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection; from whence wee may gather, that the wife being as the mans owne body, may be beaten, when ſhe will not otherwiſe be kept vnder, but be checke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate with him, that thereby ſhe may be brought into ſubiection to him.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>By beating, the Apoſtle meanes not a ſtriking, a flapping, or whipping of himſelfe, as the foppiſh Papiſts falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imagine, but a taming of his body, by abſtaining from thoſe thinges which might puffe vp his fleſh: and ſo indeed we grant, that a man in wiſedome when hee ſees the ſtoutneſſe of his wiues ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, or the pride of her heart, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of her affections ſwell, either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God or him, then, I ſay, he is to reſtraine her from thoſe thinges which might make her more malapert, and hee may then vſe ſuch holy meanes as may keepe her vnder.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Men, as</hi> Abigail <hi>ſhewed, are to loue their wiues as Chriſt loued his Church.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, but you know, though
<pb facs="tcp:7282:51"/> Chriſt loue his Church, yet if it will not be ruled by him, he will correct it, and that ſharply: ſo by your owne reaſon, is a man to loue his wife; yet if ſhee will not be obedient to him, he may correct her by Chriſts example.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Howſoeuer it is ſaid that the Lord correcteth his Church if ſhee will not be ruled by him, he doth not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by giue example or encouragement, that any man ſhould beate his wife, but it ſerueth to awe vs, leſt we offend his maieſty; neither can any doe it in that manner, nor bring profite thereby, as Chriſt doth. As for the manner of Chriſts correcting his Church, it is in loue: but neuer was it heard, that euer any man did beate his wife in loue. And againe, he ſhould doe to his wife as to himſelfe; but euery one would account him a mad man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> would beate himſelfe. Further, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church by Gods correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is made better, but the wife would bee made more vnruly and outragious by beating. We are women, &amp; haue ſome experience of theſe things.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>I thinke you rather ſpeake, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you would not haue husbands to
<pb facs="tcp:7282:52"/> vſe their authority.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They haue no ſuch authoritie, neither will we for our parts giue them occaſion to ſtraine that which they haue vpon the tenters.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>I would my wife would giue me no occaſion neither.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I ſuppoſe by your ſpéech, that you haue had many bouts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea that we haue, till the bloud hath run downe the one of our faces.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O lamentable thing to bee heard of in a Chriſtian common wealth betwéene man and wife!</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>But how much the better hath ſhe bene?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Not ſo much as I haue bene the worſe, and ſhee alſo was worſe and worſe rather.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you neighbour, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore follow our counſell though we bee but women.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ez.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What would you haue me to do?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Suppoſe now that you had ſome deformitie on your face, which did diſ-figure you ſo much, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one would be loath to looke vpon you; and if you could helpe it, what would you do?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7282:52"/>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>If that by any meanes I could helpe it, I would preſently; and if I could not, then I would couer it, that none ſhould ſee it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>So likewiſe ought you to deale with your wife, for ſhee is a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all member of your body, yea as hath bene ſaid, ſhee is as your ſelfe; therefore as you helpe the deformitie of your owne face, or if you can not heale it, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it, ſo muſt you do vnto your wiues deformities. Againe, if you had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſome filthy and abhominable ſinne which were not to be named, and there were onely one or two that did know it, what would you doe in ſuch a caſe?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>Surely, if poſſible I could, I would ſtoppe their mouthes that they ſhould not vtter it, leſt I ſhould bee ſhamed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why then, if your wife com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit not ſuch vgly offences, how much more ought you to keepe ſilence? and though one or two know of it, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate them to make no words? ſeeing you haue confeſſed, that the more vgly and grieuous your offences are, the
<pb facs="tcp:7282:53"/> more carefull you would bée, leſt they ſhould be ſpread abroad: therefore the more your wiues infirmities are, the more you are to doe the office of a good phyſition; euen to labour to cure them; &amp; if you cannot, at leaſt to couer them, as it is written:</hi> Vpon your vncomely members, put more comelineſſe on, <hi>the which may not vnfitly bee applied to this matter. Thy wife is one of thy principall members; if ſhe bée vncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly any way, put thou more comlineſſe on; if ſhee be not ſo beautifull, as thou deſireſt, couer it with contentation; if not ſo prouident as ſhee ought, couer that with thy good husbandry; if ſhe bée not ſo wiſe, as thou wiſheſt, couer that with thy prudency.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If ſhee be not ſo louing as is fit, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer that with the ſkirts of thy loue; if cholericke, couer it with patience: and although ſhee faile in dutie, which ſhee ought, yet ſhée may challenge yours as due debt, as long as ſhee is your wife you are bound to giue honour to her as to the weaker veſſell.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>If theſe things were well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of many men, much ſtrife and
<pb facs="tcp:7282:53"/> terrible broiles would be left betweene man and wife.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yea, but I muſt needs tel you that theſe things can hardly be digeſted; for if wee ſhould yeeld thus much to our wiues, they would make ſtarke fooles of vs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>No, not ſo ſir, for you ſhoud ſee the bleſſing of God vpon you, which would mitigate the ſwelling and raging of your wiues affections. I pray you tell me ſir, ſay that you had a ſoare arme grieuouſly wounded, or had drunke a cup of poyſon, or were ſicke neere vnto death, what would you do in theſe caſes?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If I had a ſoare, I would haue a ſalue according to the nature and big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the wound; or if I had drunke poyſon, I would preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſéeke a reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to expell it; or if I were ſicke néere vnto death, I would aske the counſell of the phyſition, and follow the ſame, and the more ſicke that I ſhould bee, the more would I make of my ſelfe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>Euen ſo you muſt do to your wife; the greater that her ſoare is, the better your ſalue muſt be, and the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:7282:54"/> her wound is, the more muſt bee your plaiſter, and the skilfuller ſurgian is required; and the more her ſickenes is, the more carefull &amp; tender you muſt be ouer her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Neither paines, care, nor coſt ſhould be wanting, if I were in hope to do her good.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>The captaine cannot promiſe his ſouldiers victory, before they fight; nor the phyſition his patient health, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he miniſter vnto him: but yet Chriſt Ieſus our captaine hath promiſed you victory, if that you will be directed by him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes, with all my heart.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>This then is your precept, that you loue your wife as hee did his Church.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I will try, if that I can win her by kindneſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>That muſt bee the way, if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you win her, and the meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you muſt keepe her being won. Now ſeeing wee haue proceeded thus farre, if you pleaſe I will you ſhew the cauſes, as I haue heard of a learned and godly man, wherfore the husband ſhould loue
<pb facs="tcp:7282:54"/> his wife.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Do ſo then with a good will, and I would euery cauſe were a cord to tie mée vnto it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>The cauſes are ſo weighty, yea euery one of them ſo mightie, that they may not onely be termed hempe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cords, but rather ſtrong yron chaines to tie &amp; bind not onely you, but euery man to his wife, in the vnſeparable knot of loue. The firſt is becauſe ſhe is the creature of God, made of the ſame matter and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that you are. The ſecond is, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhee is your wife; and the third is, becauſe ſhee either is, or may be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. Now for the firſt, for that ſhee is the creature of God made of the ſame matter and nature that your ſelfe is, you are to loue her, though ſhee be your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimie; as it is written: <hi>Loue your enimies;</hi> that is, as they are the creatures of God, &amp; made in his image, not for their owne ſakes: yet for Gods ſake. Secondly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe is your wife: <hi>For this cauſe ſhal a man leaue father and mother, and cleaue to his wife, and they ſhall be one fleſh.</hi> This doth ſo glue and ioyne man and wife together that no vnkindneſſe or wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:7282:55"/> (except adultery) ought to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate them. The third cauſe that ought to ioyne man and wife in affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, is in that ſhe either is or may be a Chriſtian: if that ſhe be, then you are to loue her, for that ſhee is called vnto the ſame profeſſion, baptized with the ſame baptiſme, ſanctified and renewed by the ſame Spirit, bought with the ſame price, partaker of the ſame hope, faith, and communion of Saints, and of the ſame graces, and heauenly riches in Chriſt Ieſus, and made heire of one and the ſame kingdome of glorie, for euer to reigne with God and his Chriſt, in the preſence of his holy Angles world without end. Theſe things I ſay ought to cauſe a man to loue his wife, to che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, maintaine, and prouide for her like a woman, &amp; to comfort her, as his owne bowels. Now where this true loue is, there wil nothing, that is either neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, profitable, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable for the wife bee wanting, if that poſſible her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band can procure it; &amp; I would all hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands would marke this. For accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his loue, will his care be, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for her; and after his care, will his
<pb facs="tcp:7282:55"/> diligence bee to pleaſe her; and as hee pleaſeth her, ſo ſhall hee haue comfort by her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This may ſerue to reproue the corrupt, proud, &amp; churliſh affections of many men, which will rather ſeeke to croſſe them in that which is good and godly.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>It is true, and much more are they to blame, that tirannouſly will rule yea ouerrule, and that without all rule, credit, or honeſtie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now I perceiue neighhour, that your name &amp; nature doe agrée well together.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſhould I doe? I muſt needes ſpeake the truth, and that which I haue knowne by mine owne experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; for I haue bene much inclined to offend this way, God forgiue me, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo, whom I know haue bene twice as bad, as my ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The worſe they are this way, the worſe it is for themſelues; for as it is ſaid, the haſty man neuer wants woe, ſo I thinke I may ſay, the tyrant ſhall neuer want a ſhrew.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>I would ſuch men would but
<pb facs="tcp:7282:56"/> a little conſider how the Lord doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tigate their authority ouer their wiues, when he ſaith, that they ſhould honour them as the weaker veſſels. And againe, that man and wife make but one body; and againe, that they ſhould draw the yoke equally together.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Your wiſh is very good</hi> Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gail; <hi>for want of due conſideration is the neglect of true practiſe of all duties.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>And truely neighbours it comes to my minde now, that the Lord laid theſe duties of louing &amp; honoring their wiues vpon men, partly becauſe they are ſtronger and more able to beare and ſupport the infirmities and weakeneſſes of their wiues, then the wiues are of the husbands. And againe, that the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands ſhould not ſwell too much with their authority, that they ſhould not make their poores wiues as ſlaues, but ſhould account of them as themſelues. For the Lord knew very well that men are of ſuch natures (for the moſt part) that if hee gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> power, they would ſtretch it to the vttermoſt: and therefore he abates their ſuperiority, and makes it in ſome meaſure equal with the wiues.
<pb facs="tcp:7282:56"/> And further he would haue ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to know that this is his dignity to giue honour vnto the woman, leſt ſhee through the loftineſſe of his minde ſhould bee vſed croſly and vnkindly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lo neighbour, lo, yonder comes your wife.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>Why how now wife, where haue you bene all this while?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Forſooth husband, I haue bene about ſome ſpeciall buſineſſe, that concerns you and me.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>Why didſt thou ſtay ſo long?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I pray you good husband be not offended with mee, and I will tell you.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>I am glad, that you are ſo humble and courteous; if you hold on thus <hi>Xantip,</hi> I hope that wee ſhall neuer fall out.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I hope that I ſhall not onely continue, but increaſe in doing my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty both to God and you.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>And then I make no doubt, but my loue ſhall be more and more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended vnto thee: come and ſit downe here, and tell me, where haſt thou bene?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If it ſhall pleaſe you husband,
<pb facs="tcp:7282:57"/> I haue bene much troubled in my mind ſince I went foorth, for ſome iars that haue bene betwéene vs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>And I haue bene much quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and comforted in my mind, wife, ſince thy comming in, for the peace which I hope ſhall be betweene vs: but proceede and ſay one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As I was comming home, I ſpied a ſolitarie place, which I went vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, &amp; there powred forth my complaints to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, praying his maieſty for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of my diſobedience towards you, &amp; al my abuſing of you with my tong by railing ſpeeches, and that wee might more quietly liue together then we had done; for I felt ſuch horrible gripings within me, that I thought my heart would haue burſt: and then came the trifling occaſions of my falling out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my minde, which made ſuch horrible broiles and hurly burly betweene vs, the which at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt I might haue ſtopt with a patient word; but ſinfull wretch y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I was, I rather opened a fountaine, by my railing tong. And thus as I was bewailing my miſerable eſtate, &amp; thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king what a hell it was, for man &amp; wife
<pb facs="tcp:7282:57"/> to be at ods, there comes by Maiſter T, who ſeeing me all alone, aſked me what I did ſo ſolitary. I could ſcarce ſpeake to him for wéeping. He ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſked me what I ailed, ſaying merrily it was more ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to ſée me wéepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fight; &amp; further aſkt if we had faln out, &amp; now I had got y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foile? I told him no, we were not falne out, but I was much grieued that we could kéepe no more in; at which words he wondred, and yet reioyced to ſée me mourne. And when hee perceiued that I was much afflicted in ſpirit for my of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, he comforted me with theſe and ſuch like words, ſaying:</hi> Bleſſed are they that mourne, for they ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted. Bleſſed are they that go on their way weeping, for they ſhall returne, and bring their ſheaues with them. <hi>And ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed vnto me the ſwéete promiſes of God in Chriſt Ieſus, ſaying, Chriſt ſaith:</hi> Come vnto me ye that are thirſty, &amp; buy of me wine without ſiluer. <hi>And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine:</hi> If any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin, we haue an aduocate with the Father, Chriſt Ieſus the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. <hi>And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I cryed, I haue ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; more againſt God, what ſhall I doe? what ſhall I doe? he
<pb facs="tcp:7282:58"/> would bid me poſſeſſe my ſoule in pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and beléeue in the Lord Ieſus, and take hold of his mercies by the hand of Faith, and then, though my ſins were as redde as ſcarlet, they ſhould bee as white as woolle; and that the Lord tooke no pleaſure in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſtruction of ſinners; but if they would turne from their euill wayes vnto him, and continue in well doing vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end, they ſhould vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly be ſaued. And when he had ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what pacified my wounded ſpirit, hee perſwaded me to go with him to a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. I pauſed a little, but at laſt went with him, in a bleſſed howre I thank my God: for I reaped more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and comfort thereat, then euer I did at any before.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>The cauſe, neighbour <hi>Xantip,</hi> or rather the fault I may ſay, hath bene in your ſelfe heretofore, in that you haue not gone ſo humbled, and with an vnfeigned deſire to know, and doe your duty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I acknowledge it to be ſo, good neighbour</hi> Abigail, <hi>and I pray God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue me that, and all my other ſins.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>God hath promiſed to forgiue
<pb facs="tcp:7282:58"/> all that vnfeignedly repent, of whom I make no doubt, by that I haue now heard from your owne mouth, that you are one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eul.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What did y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Preacher handle?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>He ſpake of the mutuall duties of man and wife, and of both their duties towards God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That was moſt excellent do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine for vs, wife.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea indeede husband, I thanke God, it was moſt profitable, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, I wiſhed you many a time there.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I thanke God and our good neighbours, we haue bene well exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed here this afternoone alſo: for I hope they haue done me more good then euer I thought women could haue done to man in that kinde.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>I thanke God alſo for it, and I reioyce at it in my ſoule.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Well wife, here is my hand, and giue me thine, and let vs renew our couenant which wee haue broken with God, and toward each other. And now let vs here vow both before God and our good neighbours,</hi> Abigail <hi>and</hi> Eula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,
<pb facs="tcp:7282:59"/> 
                     <hi>through his grace to keepe the ſame inuiolate while we liue.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Xant.</speaker>
                  <p>Here husband, here is both my hand and my heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abig.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bleſſed &amp; praiſed bee our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious God for his excéeding mercy now ſhewed to you both: and I beſéech his Maieſtie that you may both kéepe your couenant with him, and one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther while breath is in your bodies; that when it ſhall be his pleaſure to take you hence, hee may receiue your ſoules and bodies into his glorious kingdome.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ezer.</speaker>
                  <p>And bleſſed are you, which through Gods mercy haue bene ſpeciall inſtruments to do vs good; and I with my wife, accordingly as we are bound, will not ceaſſe to praiſe God, and to pray to him for you, that hee would of his rich grace preſerue and bleſſe you both, with vs and all the reſt that loue the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, to whom be all praiſe and thanks for euer. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:7282:59"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
